<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The soveraignty &amp; goodness of God, together, with the faithfulness of his promises displayed; being a narrative of the captivity and restauration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson. Commended by her, to all that desires to know the Lords doing to, and dealings with her. Especially to her dear children and relations, / written by her own hand for her private use, and now made publick at the earnest desire of some friends, and for the benefit of the afflicted.</title>
            <author>Rowlandson, Mary White, ca. 1635-ca. 1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09906</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 55716986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Evans 332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">55716986</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 55716986</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1800:6, 1641-1700 , 2915:8a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The soveraignty &amp; goodness of God, together, with the faithfulness of his promises displayed; being a narrative of the captivity and restauration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson. Commended by her, to all that desires to know the Lords doing to, and dealings with her. Especially to her dear children and relations, / written by her own hand for her private use, and now made publick at the earnest desire of some friends, and for the benefit of the afflicted.</title>
                  <author>Rowlandson, Mary White, ca. 1635-ca. 1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second addition [sic] corrected and amended.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge [Mass.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at 1800:6 stained, and torn, with loss of text; t.p. and preface bound at end.</note>
                  <note>No copy of a first edition is known. Cf. Evans.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (1800:6) and Boston Public Library (2915:8a).</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 2915:8a with: The possibility of Gods forsaking a people ... / By Mr. Joseph Rowlandson. Boston in New-England : Printed for John Ratcliffe, &amp; John Griffin., 1682.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rowlandson, Mary White, ca. 1635-ca. 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Indians of North America --  Massachusetts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>King Philip's War, 1675-1676 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>United States --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192319:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192319:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192319:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Soveraignty &amp; Goodneſs</hi> OF GOD, Together, With the Faithfulneſs of His Promiſes Diſplayed; Being a NARRATIVE Of the <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>Restauration</hi> of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> Mary Rowlandſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Commended by her, to all that deſires to know the Lords doings to, and dealings with Her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſpecially to her dear Children and Relations,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Addition Corrected and amended.</p>
            <p>Written by Her own Hand for Her private Uſe, and now made Publick at the earneſt Deſire of ſome Friends, and for the benefit of the Afflicted.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 32.29,</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>See now that I, even I am he, and there is no God with me: I kill and I make alive, I wound and I heal neither is there any can deliver out of my hand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Green,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:192319:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192319:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Preface to the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was on <hi>Tueſday, Feb.</hi> 1. 1675. in the afternoon, when the <hi>Narrhaganſets</hi> quarters (in or toward the <hi>Nipmug</hi> Country, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are now retyred for fear of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army lying in their own Country) were the ſecond time beaten up by the Forces of the united Colonies, who thereupon ſoon betook themſelves to flight, and were all the next day purſued by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſome overtaken and deſtroyed, But on <hi>Thurſday,</hi> Feb. 3. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> having now been ſix dayes on their march, from their he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d quarters, at <hi>Wickford,</hi> in the <hi>Narrhaganſet</hi> Country, toward, and after the Enemy, and proviſion grown exceeding ſhort, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they were fain to kill ſome Horſes for the ſupply, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of their <hi>Indian</hi> friends, they were neceſſitated to conſider what was beſt to be done: And about noon (having hitherto followed the chaſe as hard as they might) a Councill was called, and though ſome few were of another mind, yet it was concluded by far the greater part of the Councill of War, that the Army ſhould deſiſt the purſuit, and retire: the Forces of <hi>Plimouth</hi> and the <hi>Bay</hi> to the next Town of the <hi>Bay,</hi> and <hi>Connecticut</hi> Forces to their own next Towns: Which determination was immediately put in execution. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent whereof, as it was not difficult to be foreſeen by thoſe that knew the cauſleſs enmity of theſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the malicious and revengefull ſpirit of theſe Heathen: ſo it ſoon proved diſmall.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Narrhaganſets</hi> were now driven quite from their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and all their proviſions there hoarded up, to which they durſt not at preſent return, and being ſo numerous as they were, ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured thoſe to whom they went, whereby both the one and other were now reduced to extream ſtraits, and ſo neceſſitated to take the firſt and beſt opportunity for ſupply, and very glad, no doubt of ſuch an opportunity as this, to provide for themſelves, and make ſpoil of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at once; and ſeeing themſelves thus diſcharged of their purſuers, and a little refreſhed after their flight, the very next week on <hi>Thurſeday, Feb.</hi> 10. they fell with mighty force and fury upon <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> which ſmall Town, remote from aid of others, and not being Geriſoned as it might, the Army being now come in, and as the time indeed required (the deſign of the <hi>Indians</hi> againſt
<pb facs="tcp:192319:4"/>that place being known to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſome time before) was not able to make effectual reſiſtance: but notwithſtanding utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Inhabitants, moſt of the buildings were turned into aſhes; many People (Men, Women and Children) ſlain, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers captivated. The moſt ſolemn and remarkable part of this Trajedy, may that juſtly be reputed, which fell upon the Family of that reverend Servant of God, Mr. <hi>Joſeph Rolandſon,</hi> the faithfull Paſtor of Chriſt in that place, who being gone down to the Councill of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſachuſets</hi> to ſeek aid for the defence of the place, at his return found the Town in flames, or ſmoke, his own houſe being ſer on fire by the Enemy, through the diſadvantage of a defective Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and all in it conſumed: his precious yoke-fellow, and dear Children, wounded and captivated (as the iſſue evidenced, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Narrative declares) by theſe cruel and barbarous Salvages. A ſad Cateſtrophe! Thus all things come alike to all: None knows either love or hatred by âll that is before him. It is no new thing for Gods precions ones to drink as deep as others, of the Cup of common Calamity: Take juſt <hi>Lot</hi> (yet captivated) for inſtance beſide others. But it is not my buſineſs to dilate on theſe things, but only in few words introductively to preface to the following ſcript, which is a Narrative of the wonderfully awfull, wiſe, holy, powerfull, and gracious providence of God, towards that worthy and precious Gentle woman, the dear Conſort of the ſaid Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Rowlandſon,</hi> and her Children with her, as in caſting of her into ſuch a waterleſs pit, ſo in preſerving, ſupporting, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying thorow ſo many ſuch extream hazards, unſpeakable difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and diſconſolateneſs, and at laſt delivering her out of them all, and her ſurviving Children alſo. It was a ſtrange and amazing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, that the Lord ſhould ſo afflict his precious Servant, and Hand maid: It was as ſtrange, if not more, that he ſhould ſo bear up the ſpirits of his Servant under ſuch bereavments, and or his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid under ſuch captivity, travels and hardſhips (much too hard for fleſh and blood) as he did, and at length deliver and reſtore But he was their Saviour, who hath ſaid, <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the Waters, I will be with thee, and thorough the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: When thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e burnt, nor ſhall the flame kindle upon thee,</hi> Iſa. 93. ver. 2. and again. <hi>He woundeth and his hands make whole. He ſhall deliver thee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, yea in ſeven there ſhall no evil touch thee: In Famine he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem thee from Death, and in War from the power if the ſword,</hi> Job 5.18, 19, 20. Methinks this diſpenſation doth bear ſome reſemblance to thoſe of <hi>Joſeph, David</hi> and <hi>Daniel;</hi> yea, and of the three Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren too, the Stories whereof do repreſent us with the excellent tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of divine providence, curious pieces of divine work: and truly ſo doth this, and therefore not to be forgotten, but worthy to be exhibited to, and viewed, and pondered by all, that diſdain not to conſider the operation of his hands.</p>
            <p>The works of the Lord (not only of Creation, but of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nce alſo, eſpecially thoſe that do more peculiarly concern his
<pb facs="tcp:192319:4"/>dear ones, that are as the Apple of his Eye, as the Signet upon Hi Hand, the Delight of his Eyes, and the Object of his tendereſt Care) and great, ſought out of all thoſe that have pleaſure therein. And of theſe verily this is none of the leaſt.</p>
            <p>This Narrative was penned by the Gentlewoman her ſelf, to be to her a memorandum of Gods dealing with her, that ſhe might never forget, but remember the ſame, &amp; the ſeverall circumſtances there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all the dayes of her life. A pious ſcope which deſerves both commendation and imitation: Some friends having obtained a ſight of it, could not but be ſo much affected with the many paſſages of working providence diſcovered therein, as to judge it worthy of publick view, and altogether unmeet that ſuch works of God ſhould be hid from preſent and future Generations: And therefore though this Gentlewomans modeſty would not thruſt it into the Preſs, yet her gratitude unto God made her not hardly perſwadable to let it paſs, that God might have his due glory, and others bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by it as well as her ſelf. I hope by this time none will caſt any reflection upon this Gentlewoman, on the ſcore of this publication of her affliction and deliverance. If any ſhould, doubtleſs they may be reckoned with the nine lepers, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Were there not ten cleanſed, where are the nine? but one returning to give God thanks.</hi> Let ſuch further know that this was a diſpenſation of publick note, and of univerſall concernment, and ſo much the more, by how much the nearer this Gentlewoman ſtood related to that faithfull Servant of God, whoſe capacity and employment was publick in the houſe of God, and his name on that account of a very ſweet ſavour in the Churches of Chriſt, who is there of a true Chriſtian ſpirit, that did not look upon himſelf much concerned in this bereavment, this Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity in the time thereof, and in his deliverance when it came, yea more then in many others; and how many are there, to whom ſo concerned, it will doubtleſs be a very acceptable thing to ſee the way of God with this Gentlewoman in the aforeſaid diſpenſation, thus laid out and pourtrayed before their eyes.</p>
            <p>To conclude whatever any coy phantaſies may deem, yet it highly concerns thoſe that have ſo deeply taſted, how good the Lord is, to enquire with <hi>David, What ſhall I render to the Lord for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits to me. Pſal.</hi> 116.12. He thinks nothing too great; yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible of his own diſproportion to the due praiſes of God he cals in help. <hi>Oh, magnifie the Lord with me, let us exalt his Name together, Pſal.</hi> 34.3 And it is but reaſon, that out praiſes ſhould hold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with our prayers: and that as many hath helped together by prayer for the obtaining of his Mercy, ſo praiſes ſhould be returned by many on this behalf; And foraſmuch as not the generall but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular knowledge of things makes deepeſt impreſſion upon the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, this Narrative particularizing the ſeveral paſſages of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence will nor a little conduce thereunto. And therefore holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in order to the attainment of that end, accounts himſelf concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to declare what God had done for his ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16. <hi>Come and hear, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l ye that fear God, and I will declare what God hath done for
<pb facs="tcp:192319:5"/>my ſoul,</hi> i. e. <hi>for his life,</hi> ſee v. 9, 10. <hi>He holdeth our ſoul in life, and ſuffers not our feet to be moved, for thou our God haſt proved us, thou haſt tryed us, as ſilver is tryed.</hi> Life-mercies, are heart-affecting-mercies, of great impreſſion and force, to enlarge pious hearts in the praiſes of God, ſo that ſuch know not how but to talk of Gods acts, and to ſpeak of and publiſh his wonderfull works. Deep troubles, when the waters come in unto thy ſoul, are wont to produce vowes: vowes muſt be paid, <hi>It is better not vow, than vow and not to pay.</hi> I may ſay, that as none knows what it is to fight and purſue ſuch an enemy as this, but they that have fought and purſued them: ſo none can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what it is to be captivated, and enſlaved to ſuch atheiſticall proud, wild, cruel, barbarous, bruitiſh (in one word) diabolicall creatures as theſe, the worſt of the heathen; nor what difficulties, hardſhips, hazards, ſorrows, anxieties and perplexities do unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably wait upon ſuch a condition, but thoſe that have tryed it. No ſerieus ſpirit then (eſpecialiy knowing any thing of this Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans piety) can imagine but that the vows of God are upon her. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her then if ſhe come thus into publick, to pay thoſe vows. Come and hear what ſhe hath to ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am confident that no Friend of diviné Providence will ever repent his time and pains, ſpent in reading over theſe ſheets, but will judg them worth peruſing again and again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear <hi>Reader,</hi> you may ſee an inſtance of the Soveraignty of God, who doth what he will with his own as well as others; and who may ſay to him, <hi>What dofl thou?</hi> Here you may ſee an inſtance of the faith and patience of the Saints, under the moſt heart-ſinking tryals; here you may ſee, the promiſes are breaſts full of conſolation, when all the world beſides is empty, and gives nothing but ſorrow. That God is indeed the ſupream Lord of the world, ruling the moſt unruly, weakening the moſt cruel and ſalvage, granting hir People mercy in the ſight of the unmercifull, curbing the luſts of the moſt filthy, holding the hands of the violent, delivering the prey from the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>and gathering together the out caſts of</hi> Iſrael. Once and again you have heard, but hear you may ſee, <hi>that power belongeth unto God;</hi> that our God is the God of Salvation, and to him belong the iſſues from Death. That our God is in the Heavens, and doth what ever pleaſes him. Here you have <hi>Sampſon</hi> Riddle examplified, and that great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. verified, <hi>Out of the Eater comes forth meat, and ſweetneſs out of the ſtrong;</hi> The worſt of evils working together for the beſt good. How evident is it that the Lord hath made this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman a gainer by all this affliction, that ſhe can ſay, <hi>'tis good for her, yea better that ſhe hath been, then that ſhe ſhould not have been, thus afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Ob how doth God ſhine forth in ſuch things as theſe;<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou getteſt no good by ſuch a Declaration as this, the fault muſt needs be tbine own. Read therefore, Peruſe, Ponder, and from hence lay up ſomething from the experience of another, againſt thine own turn comes, that ſo thou alſo through patience and conſolation of the Scripture mayeſt have hope.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>PER AMICAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192319:5"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the <hi>CAPTIVITY AND</hi> REST A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATION OF Mrs. Mary Rowlandſon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the tenth of <hi>February</hi> 1675. Came the <hi>Indians</hi> with great numbers upon <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> Their firſt coming was about Sun-riſing; hearing the noiſe of ſome Guns, we looked out; ſeveral Houſes were burning, and the Smoke aſcending to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. There were five perſons taken in one houſe, the Father, and the Mother and a ſucking Child, they knockt on the head; the other two they took and carried away alive. Their were two others, who being out of their Gariſon upon ſome occaſion were ſet upon; one was knockt on the head, the other eſcaped: Another their was who running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong was ſhot and wounded, and ſell down; he pegged of them his life, promiſing them Money (as they told me) but they would not hearken to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192319:6"/>him but knockt him in head, and ſtript him naked, and ſplit open his Bowels. Another ſeeing many of the <hi>Indians</hi> about his Barn, ventured and went out, but was quickly ſhot down. There were three others belonging to the ſame Gariſon who were killed; the <hi>Indians</hi> getting up upon the roof of the Barn, had advantage to ſhoot down upon them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Fortification. Thus theſe murtherous wretches went on, burning, and deſtroying before them,</p>
            <p>At length they came and beſet our own houſe, and quickly it was the dolefulleſt day that ever mine eyes ſaw. The Houſe ſtood upon the edg of a hill; ſome of the <hi>Indians</hi> got behind the hill, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into the Barn, and others behind any thing that could ſhelter them; from all which places they ſhot againſt the Houſe, ſo that the Bullets ſeemed to fly like hail; and quickly they wounded one man among us, then another, and then a third, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two hours (according to my obſervation, in that amazing time) they had been about the houſe before they prevailed to fire it (which they did with Flax and Hemp, which they brought out of the Barn, and there being no deſence about the Houſe, only two Flankers at two oppoſite corners, and one of them not finiſhed) they fired it once, and one ventured out and quenched it, but they quickly fired it again, and that took. Now is that dreadfull hour come, that I have often heard of (in time of War, as it was the caſe of others) but now mine eyes ſee it. Some in our houſe were fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192319:6"/>for their lives, others wallowing in their blood, the Houſe on fire over our heads, and the bloody Heathen ready to knock us on the head, if we ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our: Now might we hear Mothers &amp; Children crying out for themſelves, and one another, <hi>Lord, What ſhall we do?</hi> Then I took my Children (and one of my ſiſters, hers) to go forth and leave the houſe: but as ſoon as we came to the dore and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, the <hi>Indians</hi> ſhot ſo thick that the bulletts rattled againſt the Houſe, as if one had taken an handfull of ſtones and threw them, ſo that we were fain to give back. We had ſix ſtout Dogs belonging to our Garriſon, but none of them would ſtir, though another time, if any <hi>Indian</hi> had come to the door, they were ready to fly upon him and tear him down. The Lord hereby would make us the more to acknowledge his hand, and to ſee that our help is alwayes in him. But out we muſt go, the fire increaſing, and coming along behind us, roaring, and the <hi>Indians</hi> gaping before us with their Guns, Spears and Hatchets to devour us. No ſooner were we out of the Houſe, but my Brother in Law (being before wounded, in defending the houſe, in or near the throat) fell down dead, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the <hi>Indians</hi> ſcornfully ſhouted, and hallowed, and were preſently upon him, ſtripping off his cloaths, the bulletts flying thick, one went through my ſide, and the ſame (as would ſeem) through the bowels and hand of my dear Child in my arms. One of my elder Siſters Children, named <hi>William,</hi> had then his Leg broken, which the <hi>Indians</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192319:7"/>they knockt him on head. Thus were we butchered by thoſe mercileſs Heathen, ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, with the blood running down to our heels. My eldeſt Siſter being yet in the Houſe, and ſeeing thoſe wofull ſights, the Infidels haling Mothers one way, and Children another, and ſome wallowing in their blood: and her elder Son telling her that her Son <hi>William</hi> was dead, and my ſelf was wounded, ſhe ſaid, And, <hi>Lord let medy with them;</hi> which was no ſooner ſaid, but ſhe was ſtruck with a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and ſell down dead over the threſhold. I hope ſhe is reaping the fruit of her good labours, being faithfull to the ſervice of God in her place. In her younger years ſhe lay under much trouble upon ſpiritual accounts, till it pleaſed God to make that precious Scripture take hold of her heart, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>And be ſaid unto me my Grace is ſufficient for thee.</hi> More then twenty years after I have heard her tell how ſweet and comfortable that place was to her, But to return: The <hi>Indians</hi> laid hold of us, pulling me on way, and the Children another, and ſaid, <hi>Come go along with us;</hi> I told them they would kill me: they anſwered, <hi>If I were willing to go along with them, they would not hurt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh the dolefull ſight that now was to behold at this Houſe! <hi>Come, behold the works of the Lord, what diſſolations he has made in the Earth.</hi> Of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven perſons who were in this one Houſe, none eſcaped either preſent death, or a bitter captivity, ſave only one, who might ſay as he. <hi>Job</hi> 1.15. <hi>And I only am eſcaped alone to tell the News.</hi> There
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192319:7"/>were twelve killed, ſome ſhot, ſome ſtab'd with their Spears, ſome knock'd down with their Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets. When we are in proſperity, Oh the little that we think of ſuch dreadfull ſights, and to ſee our dear Friends, and Relations ly bleeding out their heart-blood upon the ground. There was one who was chopt into the head with a Hatchet, and ſtript naked, and yet was crawling up and down. It is a ſolemn ſight to ſee ſo many Chriſtians lying in their blood, ſome here, and ſome there, like a company of Sherp torn by Wolves. All of them ſtript naked by a company of hell-hounds, roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſinging, ranting and inſulting, as if they would have torn our very hearts out; yet the Lord by his Almighty power preſerved a number of us from death, for there were twenty-four of us taken alive and carried Captive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I had of ten before this ſaid, that if the</hi> Indians <hi>ſhould come, I ſhould chuſe rather to be killed by them then taken alive</hi> but when it came to the tryal my mind changed; their glittering weapons ſo daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſpirit, that I choſe rather to go along with thoſe (as I may ſay) ravenous Beats, then that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to end my dayes; and that I may the better declare what happened to me during that grievous Captivity I ſhall particularly ſpeak of the ſeverall Removes we had up and down the Wilderneſs.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt Remove.</head>
               <p>Now away we muſt go with thoſe Barbarous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192319:8"/>Creatures, with our bodies wounded and bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and our hearts no leſs than our bodies. About a mile we went that night, up upon a hill within ſight of the Town where they intended to lodge. There was hard by a vacant houſe (deſerted by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh before, for fear of the <hi>Indians</hi>] I asked them whither I might not lodge in the houſe that night? to which they anſwered, what will you love <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men</hi> ſtill? this was the dolefulleſt night that ever my eyes ſaw. Oh the roaring, and ſinging and danceing, and yelling of thoſe black creatures in the night, which made the place a lively reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of hell. And as miſerable was the waſt that was there made, of Horſes, Cuttle, Sheep, Swine, Galves, Lambs, Roaſting Pigs, and Fowls [which they bad plundered in the Town] ſome roaſting, ſome lying and burning, and ſome boyling to feed our mercileſs Enemles; who were joyfull enough though we were diſconſolate. To add to the dolefulneſs of the former day, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malneſs of the preſent night: my thoughts ran up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my loſſes and ſad bereaved condition. All was gone, my Huſband gone (at leaſt ſeparated from me, he being in the Bay; and to add to my grief, the <hi>Indians</hi> told me they would kill him as he came homeward) my Children gone, my Relations and Friends gone, our Houſe and home and all our comforts within door, and without, all was gone, (except my life) and I knew not but the next moment that might go too. There remained nothing to me but one poor wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192319:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and it ſeemed at preſent worſe than death that it was in ſuch a pitiful condition, beſpeaking, Compaſſion, and I had an refreſhing for it, nor ſuitable things to revive it, Little do many think what is the ſavageneſs and bruitiſhneſs of this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Enemy! even thoſe that ſeem to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs more than others among them, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have fallen into their hands.</p>
               <p>Thoſe ſeven that were killed at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> the ſummer before upon a Sabbath day, and the one that was afterward killed upon a week day, were ſtain and mangled in a barbarous manner, by one-ey'd <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Marlborough's</hi> Praying <hi>Indians,</hi> which Capt. <hi>Moſely</hi> brought to <hi>Boſton,</hi> as the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> told me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But now, the next morning, I muſt turn my back upon the Town, and travel with them into the vaſt and iſolate Wilderneſs, I knew not whether.</hi> It is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tongue, or pen can expreſs the ſorrows of my heart, and bitterneſs of my ſpirit, that <hi>I</hi> had at this departure: but God was with me, in a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull manner, carrying me along, and bearing up my ſpirit, that it did not quite fail One of the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> carried my poor wounded Babe upon a horſe, it went moaning all along, I ſhall dy, I ſhall dy. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> went on foot after it, with ſorrow that cannot be expreſt. At length I took it off the horſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed it in my armes till my ſtrength ſailed, and <hi>I</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192319:9"/>fell down with it: Then they ſet me upon a horſe with my wounded Child in my lap, and there being no furnitunre upon the horſe back; as we were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down a ſteep hill, we both fell over the horſes head, at which they like inhumane creatures laught, and rejoyced to ſee it, though I thought we ſhould there have ended our dayes, as overcome with ſo many difficulties. But the Lord renewed my ſtrength ſtill, and carried me along, that I might ſee more of his Power; yea, ſo much that I could never have thought of, had I not experienced it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After this it quickly began to ſnow, and when night came on, they ſtopt: and now down I muſt ſit in the ſnow, by a little fire, and a few boughs behind me, with my ſick Child in my lap; and calling much for water, being now (through the wound) fallen into a violent Fever.</hi> My own wound alſo grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſtiff, that I could ſcarce ſit down or riſe up; yet ſo it muſt be, that I muſt ſit all this cold winter night upon the cold ſnowy ground, with my ſick Child in my armes, looking that every hour would be the laſt of its life; and having no Chriſtian friend near me, either to comfort or help me. <hi>Oh,</hi> I <hi>may ſee the wonderfull power of God, that my Spirit did not utterly ſink under my affliction: ſtill the Lord upheld me with his gracious and mercifull Spirit, and we were both alive to ſee the light of the next morning.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The morning being come, they prepared to go
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192319:9"/>their way: One of the</hi> Indians <hi>got up upon a horſe, and they ſet me up behind him, with my poor ſick Babe in my lap.</hi> A very weariſome and tedious day I had of it; what with my own wound, and my Childs being ſo exceeding ſick, and in a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table condition with her wound. It may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judged what a poor feeble condition we were in, there being not the leaſt crumb of refreſhing that came within either of our mouths, from <hi>Wedneſday</hi> night to <hi>Saturday</hi> night, except only a little cold water. This day in the afternoon, about an hour by Sun, we came to the place where they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>viz.</hi> an <hi>Indian</hi> Town, called <hi>Wenimeſſet,</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Quabaug.</hi> When we were come, Oh the number of Pagans (now mercileſs enemies) that there came about me, that I may ſay as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 27.13, <hi>I had fainted, unleſs I had believed, &amp;c.</hi> The next day was the Sabbath: I then remembred how careleſs <hi>I</hi> had been of Gods holy time: how many Sabbaths I had loſt and miſpent, and how evily I had walked in Gods ſight; which lay ſo cloſs unto my ſpirit, that it was eaſie for me to ſee how righteous it was with God to cut off the threed of my life, and caſt me out of his preſence for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Yet the Lord ſtill ſhewed mercy to me, and upheld me; and as he wounded me with one hand, ſo he healed me with the other. This day there came to me one <hi>Robbert Pepper</hi> (a man belonging to <hi>Roxbury</hi>) who was taken in Captain <hi>Beers</hi> his Fight, and had been now a conſiderable time with the <hi>Indians;</hi> and up with them almoſt as far as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:192319:10"/>
                  <hi>Albany</hi> to ſee king <hi>Philip,</hi> as he told me, and was now very lately come into theſe parts. Hearing, I ſay, that I was in this <hi>Indian</hi> Town, he obtained leave to come and ſee me. He told me, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was wounded in the leg at Captain <hi>Beers</hi> his Fight; and was not able ſome time to go, but as they carried him, and as he took Oaken leaves and laid to his wound, and through the bleſſing of God he was able to travel again. Then I took Oaken leaves and laid to my ſide, and with the bleſſing of God it cured me alſo; yet before the cure was wrought, I may ſay, as it is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.5, 6. <hi>My wounds ſtink and are corrupt, I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long. I</hi> ſat much alone with a poor wounded Child in my lap, which moaned night and day, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to revive the body, or cheer the ſpirits of her, but in ſtead of that, ſometimes one <hi>Indian</hi> would come and tell me one hour, that your Maſter will knock your Child in the head, and then a ſecond, and then a third, your Maſter will quickly knock your Child in the head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This was the comfort I had from them, miſerable comforters are ye all, as he ſaid.</hi> Thus nine dayes I ſat upon my knees, with my Babe in my lap, till my fleſh was raw again; my Child being even rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to depart this ſorrowfull world, they bade me carry it out to another Wigwam (I ſuppoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not be troubled with ſuch ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) Whither I went with a very heavy heart, and down I ſat with the picture of death in my lap.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192319:10"/>About two houtes in the night, my ſweet Babe, like a Lambe departed this life, on <hi>Feb.</hi> 18. 1675. It being about <hi>ſix yeares,</hi> and <hi>five months</hi> old. It was <hi>nine dayes</hi> from the firſt wounding, in this miſerable condition, without any refreſhing of one nature or other, except a little cold water. I cannot but take notice, how at another time I could not bear to be in the room where any dead perſon was, but now the caſe is changed; I muſt and couldly down by my dead Babe, ſide by ſide all the night after. I have thought ſince of the wonderfull goodneſs of God to me, in preſerving me in the uſe of my reaſon and ſenſes, in that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed time, that I did not uſe wicked and violent means to end my own miſerable life. In the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when they underſtood that my child was dead they ſent for me home to my Maſters Wigwam: (by my Maſter in this writing, muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Quanopin,</hi> who was a <hi>Saggamore,</hi> and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried King <hi>Phillips</hi> wives Siſter; not that be firſt took me, but I was ſold to him by another <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaganſet Indian,</hi> who took me when firſt I came out of the Gariſon <hi>I</hi> went to take up my dead child in my arms to carry it with me, but they bid me let it alone: there was no reſiſting, but goe <hi>I</hi> muſt and leave it. When <hi>I</hi> had been at my maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>wigwam,</hi> I took the firſt opportunity I could get, to go look after my dead child: when I came <hi>I</hi> askt them what they had done with it? then they told me it was upon the hill: then they went and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192319:11"/>ſhewed me where it was, where I ſaw the ground was newly digged, and there they told me they had buried it: <hi>There I left that Child in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and muſt commit it, and my ſelf alſo in this Wilderneſs-condition, to him who is above all.</hi> God having taken away this dear Child, I went to ſee my daughter <hi>Mary,</hi> who was at this ſame <hi>Indian Town,</hi> at a <hi>Wigwam</hi> not very far off, though we had little liberty or opportunity to ſee one another: ſhe was about ten years old, &amp; taken from the door at firſt by a <hi>Praying Ind</hi> &amp; afterward ſold for a gun. When I came in ſight, ſhe would fall a weeping; at which they were provoked, and would not let me come near her, but bade me be gone; which was a heart-cutting word to me. I had one Child dead, another in the Wilderneſs, I knew not where, the third they would not let me come near to: <hi>Me</hi> (as he ſaid) <hi>have ye bereaved of my Children,</hi> Joſeph <hi>is not, and</hi> Simeon <hi>is not, and ye will take</hi> Benjamin <hi>alſo, all theſe things are against me.</hi> I could not for ſtill in this condition, but kept, walking from one place to another. And as I was going along, my heart was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n overwhelm'd with the thoughts of my condition, and that I ſhould have Children, <hi>and a Nation which</hi> I <hi>knew not ruled over them.</hi> Whereupon learneſtly entreated the Lord, that he would conſider my low eſtate, and ſhew me a token for good, and if it were his bleſſed will, ſome ſign and hope of ſome relief. And indeed quickly the Lord anſwered, in ſome meaſure, my poor prayers:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192319:11"/>For as I was going up and down mourning and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting my condition, my Son came to me, and asked me how I did; I had not ſeen him before, ſince the deſtruction of the Town, and I knew not where he was, till <hi>I</hi> was informed by himſelf, that he was amongſt a ſmaller percel of <hi>Indians,</hi> whoſe place was about ſix miles off; with tears in his eyes, he asked me whether his Siſter <hi>Sarah</hi> was dead; and told me he had ſeen his Siſter <hi>Mary;</hi> and prayed me, that I would not be troubled in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerence to himſelf. The occaſion of his coming to ſee me at this time, was this: <hi>There was, as I ſaid, about ſix miles from us, a ſmal Plantation of</hi> Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>where it ſeems he had been during his Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and at this time, there were ſome Forces of the</hi> Ind. <hi>gathered out of our company, and ſome alſo from them (among whom was my Sons maſter) to go to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault and burn</hi> Medfield: <hi>In this time of the abſence of his master, his dame brought him to ſee me.</hi> I took this to be ſome gracious anſwer to my earneſt and unfeigned deſire. The next day, <hi>viz.</hi> to this, the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> returned from <hi>Medfield,</hi> all the company, for thoſe that belonged to the other ſmal company, came thorough the Town that now we were at But before they came to us, Oh! the outragious roaring and hooping that there was: They began their din about a mile before they came to us. By their noiſe and hooping they ſignified how many they had deſtroyed (which was at that time twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty three) Thoſe that were with us at home, were
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192319:12"/>gathered together as ſoon as they heard the hoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and every time that the other went over their number, theſe at home gave a ſhout, that the very Earth rung again: And thus they coutinned till thoſe that had been upon the expedition were come up to the <hi>Sagamores Wigwam;</hi> and then, Oh, the hideous inſulting and triumphing that there was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome <hi>Engliſh mens</hi> ſcalps that they had taken (as their manner it) and brought with them. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice of the wonderfull mercy of God to me in thoſe afflictions, in ſending me a Bible One of the <hi>Indians</hi> that came from <hi>Medfield</hi> fight, had brought ſome plunder, came to me, and asked me, if I would have a Bible, he had got one in his Basket, I was glad of it, and asked him, whether be thought the <hi>Indians</hi> would let me read? he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, yes; ſo I took the Bible, and in that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy time, it came into my mind to read firſt the 28. <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Deut.</hi> which I did, and when I had read it, my dark heart wrought on this manner, <hi>That there was no mercy for me, that the bleſſings were gone, and the Curſes Came in their room, and that</hi> I <hi>bad loſt my opportunity.</hi> But the Lord helped me ſtill to go one reading till <hi>I</hi> came to <hi>Chap.</hi> 30 the ſeven firſt verſes, where I ſound, <hi>There was mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy promiſed again, if we would return to him by repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and though we were ſcartered from one end of the Earth to the other, yet the Lord would gather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> together, and turn all thoſe curſes upon our Enemies,</hi> I do not deſire to live to forget this Scripture, and what comfort it was to me.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192319:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the</hi> Ind. <hi>began to talk of removing from this place, ſome one way, and ſome another.</hi> There were now beſides my ſelf nine, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captives in this place (all of them Children, except one Woman) <hi>I</hi> got an opportunity to go and take my leave of them; they being to go one way, and I another, I <hi>asked them whether they were earneſt with God for deliverance,</hi> they told me, they did as they were able, and it was ſome comfort to me, that the Lord ſtirred up <hi>Children to look to him.</hi> The Woman <hi>viz.</hi> Goodwife <hi>Joſtin</hi> told me, ſhe ſhould never ſee me again, and that ſhe could find in her heart to run away; I wiſht her not to tun away by any means, for we were near <hi>thirty miles</hi> from any <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Town,</hi> and ſhe very big with Child, and had but one week to reckon; and another Child in her Arms, two years old, and bad Rivers there were to go over, &amp; we were feeble, with our poor &amp; courſe entertainment. I had my Bible with me, I pulled it out, and asked her whether ſhe would read; we opened the Bible and lighted on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. in which Pſalm we eſpecially took notice of that, <hi>ver. alt, Wait no the Lord, Be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thine Heart, wait</hi> I <hi>ſay on the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>The fourth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now</hi> I <hi>muſt part with that little Company</hi> I <hi>had.</hi> Here I parted from my Daughter <hi>Mary,</hi> (whom I never ſaw again till <hi>I</hi> ſaw her in <hi>Dorceſter,</hi> returned from Captivity, and from four little Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192319:13"/>and Neighbours, ſome of which I never ſaw af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward: the Lord only knows the end of them. Amongſt them alſo was that poor Woman before mentioned, who came to a ſad end, as ſome of the company told me in my travel: She having much grief upon her Spirit, about her miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being ſo near her time, ſhe would be often ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Indians</hi> to let her go home; they not being willing to that, and yet vexed with her importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, gathered a great company together about her, and ſtript her naked, and ſet her in the midſt of them; and when they had ſung and danced about her (in their helliſh manner) as long as they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they knockt her on head, and the child in her arms with her: when they had done that, they made a fire and put them both into it, and told the other Children that were with them, that if they attempted to go home, they would ſerve them in like manner: The Children ſaid, ſhe did not ſhed one tear, but prayed all the while. But to return to my own Journey; we travelled about half a day or little more, and came to a deſolate place in the Wilderneſs, where there were no <hi>Wigwams</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants</hi> before; we came about the middle of the afternoon to this place; cold and wet, and ſnowy, and hungry, and weary, and no refreſhing, for man, but the cold ground to ſit on, and our poor <hi>Indian cheer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heart-aking thoughts here</hi> I <hi>had about my poor Children, who were ſcattered up and down among the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192319:13"/>wild beaſts of the forreſt:</hi> My head was light &amp; diſſey (either through hunger or hard lodging, or trouble or altogether) my knees feeble, my body raw by ſitting double night and day, that I cannot expreſs to man the affliction that lay upon my Spirit, but the Lord helped me at that time to expreſs it to himſelf. I opened my Bible to read, and the Lord brought that precious Scripture to me, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.16. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, refrain thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from tears, for thy work ſhall be rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and they ſhall come again from the land of the Enemy.</hi> This was a ſweet Cordial to me, when <hi>I</hi> ſat down, and weept ſweetly over this Scripture. At this place we continued about four dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>The fifth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The occaſion (as I thought) of their moving at this time, was, the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Army it being near and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them:</hi> For they went, as if they had gone for their lives, for ſome conſiderable way, and then they made a ſtop, and choſe ſome of their ſtouteſt men, and ſent them back to hold the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in play whilſt the reſt eſcaped: And then, <hi>like</hi> Jehu, <hi>they marched on furiouſly, with their old, and with their young: ſome carried their old decrepit mothers, ſome carried one, and ſome another.</hi> Four of them carried a great <hi>Indian</hi> upon a Bier; but going through a thick Wood with him, they were hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and could make no haſt; whereupon they took
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192319:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192319:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:192319:15"/>him upon their backs, and carried him, one at a time, till they came to <hi>Bacquaug</hi> River. Upon a <hi>Friday,</hi> a little after noon we came to this River. When all the company was come up, and were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, I thought to count the number of them, but they were ſo many, and being ſomewhat in motion, it was beyond my skil. In this travel, becauſe of my wound, I was ſomewhat favoured in my load; I carried only my knitting work and two quarts of parched meal: Being very faint I asked my miſtriſs to give me one ſpoonfull of the meal, but ſhe would not give me a taſte. They quickly ſell to cutting dry trees, to make Rafts to carry them over the river: and ſoon my turn came to go over: By the advantage of ſome bruſh which they had laid upon the Raft to ſit upon, I did not wet my foot (which many of themſelves at the other end were mid-leg deep) which cannot but be acknowledged as a favour of God to my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned body, it being a very cold time. I was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore acquainted with ſuch kind of doings or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. <hi>When thou paſſſt through the water</hi> I <hi>will be with thee, and through the Rivers th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow thee, Iſai.</hi> 43.2. A certain number of us got o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the River that night, but it was the night after the Sabbath before all the company was got over. On the <hi>Saturday</hi> they boyled an old Horſes leg which they had got) and ſo we drank of the broth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſoon as they thought it was ready, and when it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> almoſt all gone, they filled it up again.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:192319:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt week of my being among them, I hardly ate any thing; the ſecond week, I found my ſtomach grow very faint for want of ſomething; and yet it was very hard to get down their filthy traſh: but the third week, though I could think how formerly my stomach would turn againſt this or that, and I could starve and dy before I could eat ſuch things, yet they were ſweet and ſavoury to my taſte.</hi> I was at this time knitting a pair of white cotton ſtockins for my miſtriſs: and had not yet wrought upon a Sabbath day; when the Sabbath came they bade me go to work; I told them it was the Sabbath-day, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them to let me reſt, and told them I would do as much more to morrow; to which they anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, they would break my face. And here <hi>I</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice of the ſtrange providence of God in preſerving the heathen: They were many hundreds, old and young, ſome ſick, and ſome lame many had <hi>Papooſes</hi> at their backs, the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at this time with us, were <hi>Squams,</hi> and they travelled with all they had, bag and baggage, and yet they got over this River aforeſaid; and on <hi>Munday</hi> they ſet their <hi>Wigwams</hi> on fire, and away they went: On that very day came the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army after them to this River, and ſaw the ſmoak of their <hi>Wigwams,</hi> and yet this River put a ſtop to them. God did not give them courage or activity to go over after us; we were not ready for ſo great a mercy as victory and deliverance; if we had been, God would have ſound out a way for the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192319:16"/>to have paſſed this River, as well as for the <hi>Indians</hi> with their <hi>Squaws</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> and all their <hi>Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage: Oh that my People had hearkened to me, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>had walked in my ways,</hi> I <hi>ſhould ſoon have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued their Enemies, and turned my hand againſt their Adverſaries,</hi> Pſal. 81.13.14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>The ſixth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>On</hi> Munday (<hi>as</hi> I <hi>ſaid</hi>) <hi>they ſet their</hi> Wigwams <hi>on fire, and went away.</hi> It was a cold morning, and before us there was a great Brook with ice on it; ſome waded throgh it, up to the knees &amp; higher, but others went till they came to a Beaver-dam, and I amongſt them, where through the good providence of God, I did not wet my foot. <hi>I</hi> went along that day mourning and lamenting, leaving farther my own Country, and travelling into the vaſt and howling <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and I underſtood ſomething of <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife's Temptation, <hi>when ſhe looked back:</hi> we came that day to a great Swamp, by the ſide of which we took up our lodging that night. When I came to the brow of the hil, that looked toward the Swamp, I thought we had been come to a great <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Town (though there were none but our own Company) The <hi>Indians</hi> were as thick as the trees: it ſeemd as if there had been a thouſand Hatchets going at once: if one looked before one, there was nothing but <hi>Indians,</hi> and behind one, nothing but <hi>Indians,</hi> and ſo on either hand, I my ſelf in the midſt, and no Chriſtian ſoul near me, <hi>and yet how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192319:16"/>hath the Lord preſerved me inſafety? Oh the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that I have had of the goodneſs of God, to me and mine!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>The ſeventh Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>After a reſtleſs and hungry night there, we had a weariſome time of it the next day.</hi> The Swamp by which we lay, was, as it were, a deep Dungeon, and an exceeding high and ſteep hill before it. Before I got to the top of the hill, I thought my heart and legs, and all would have broken, and failed me. What through faintneſs, and ſoreneſs of body, it was a grievous day of travel to me. <hi>As we went along, I ſaw a place where</hi> Engliſh <hi>Cattle had been: that was comfort to me, ſuch as it was: quickly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that we came to an</hi> Engliſh <hi>Path, which ſo took with me, that I thought I could have freely lyan down and dyed.</hi> That day, a little after noon, we came to <hi>Squaukheag,</hi> where the <hi>Indians</hi> quickly ſpread themſelves over the deſerted <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fields, glean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they could find; ſome pickt up ears of Wheat that were crickled down, ſome found ears of <hi>Indian</hi> Corn, ſome found Ground-nuts, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſheaves of Wheat that were frozen together in the ſhock, &amp; went to threſhing of them out My ſelf got two ears of <hi>Indian</hi> Corn, and whilſt I did but turn my back, one of them was ſtolen from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which much troubled me There came an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> to them at that time, with a basket of Horſe-liver; I asked him to give me a piece: <hi>What,</hi> ſayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>can you eat Horſe-liver?</hi> I told him, I would try,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:192319:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:192319:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:192319:18"/>if he would give a piece, which he did, and I laid it on the coals to roſt; but before it was half ready, they got half of it away from me, ſo that I was fain to take the reſt and eat it as it was, with the blood about my mouth, and yet a ſavoury bit it was to me: <hi>For to the hungry Soul every bitter thing is ſweet.</hi> A ſolemn ſight methought it was, to ſee Fields of wheat and <hi>Indian</hi> Corn forſaken and ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: and the remainders of them to be food for our mercileſs Enemies. That night we had a meſs of wheat for our Supper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>The eight Remove.</head>
               <p>On the morrow morning we muſt go over the River, <hi>i. e. Connecticot,</hi> to meet with King <hi>Philip,</hi> two <hi>Cannoos</hi> full, they had carried over, the next Turn j my ſelf was to go; but as my foot was upon the <hi>Cannoo</hi> to ſtep in, there was a ſudden out-cry among them, and j muſt ſtep back; and inſtead of going over the River, j muſt go four or five miles up the River farther Northward. Some of the <hi>jndians</hi> ran one way, and ſome another. The cauſe of this rout was, as j thought, their eſpying ſome <hi>Engliſh Scouts,</hi> who were thereabout. In this travel up the River; about noon the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny made a ſtop, and ſate down; ſome to eat, and others to reſt them. As I ſate amongſt them, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of things paſt, my Son <hi>Joseph</hi> unexpectedly came to me: we asked of each others welfare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning our dolefull condition, and the change that had come upon us: We had Husbands and</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:192319:18"/>
               <p>Father, and Children, and Siſters, and Friends, and Relations, and Houſe, and Home, and many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this Life: but now we may ſay, as Job, <hi>Naked came I out of my Mothers Womb, and nak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall I return: The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> I asked him whither he would read; he told me, he earneſtly deſired it, J gave him my Bible, and he lighted upon that comfortable Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi>I ſhall not dy but live, and declare the works of the Lord: the Lord hath chaſtened me ſore, yet he hath not given me over to death.</hi> Look here, <hi>Mother</hi> (ſayes he) did you read this? And here I may take occaſion to mention one principall ground of my ſetting forth theſe Lines: even as the Pſalmiſt ſayes, <hi>To dealare the Works of the Lord,</hi> and his wonderfull Power in carrying us along, preſerving us in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> while under the Enemies hand, and returning of us in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty again. And His goodneſs in bringing to my hand ſo many comfortable and ſuitable Scriptures in my diſtreſs. But to Return, We travelled on till night; and in the morning, we muſt go over the River to <hi>Philip</hi>'s Crew. When I was in the Cannoo, I could not but be amazed at the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous crew of Pagans that were on the Bank on the other ſide. When J came aſhore, they gathered all about me, I ſitting alone in the midſt: I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved they asked one another questions, and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and rejoyced over their Gains and Victories.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:192319:19"/>
               <p>Then my heart began to fail: and I fell a weeping; which was the firſt time to my remembrance, that J wept before them. Although J had met with ſo much Affliction, and my heart was many times ready to break, yet could J not ſhed one tear in their ſight: but rather had been all this while in a maze, and like one aſtoniſhed: but now J may ſay as, <hi>Pſal</hi> 137.1. <hi>By the Rivers of</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>there we ſate down: yea, we wept when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred Zion.</hi> There one of them asked me, why J wept, J could hardly tell what to ſay: yet J an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, they would kill me: No, ſaid he, none will hurt you. Then came one of them and gave me two ſpoon-fulls of Meal to comfort me, and another gave me half a pint of Peaſe; which was more worth than many Buſhels at another time. Then J went to ſee King <hi>Philip,</hi> he bade me come in and ſit down, and asked me whether J would ſmoke it (a uſual Complement now adayes amongſt Saints and Sinners) but this no way ſuited me. For though I had formerly uſed Tobacco, yet I had left it ever ſince I was firſt taken. <hi>It ſeems to be a Bait, the Devil layes to make men looſe their precious time:</hi> J remember with ſhame, how formerly, when J had taken two or three pipes, J was preſently rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for another, ſuch a bewitching thing it is: But J thank God, he has now given me power over it: ſurely there are many who may be better imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than to ly ſucking a ſtinking Tobacco-pipe.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Indians</hi> gather their Forces to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192319:19"/>
                  <hi>North-Hampton:</hi> over-night one went about yelling and hooting to give notice of the deſign. Whereupon they fell to boyling of Ground-nuts, and parching of Corn (as many as had it) for their Proviſion: and in the morning away they went: <hi>During my abode in this place,</hi> Philip <hi>ſpake to me to make a ſhirt for his boy, which</hi> I <hi>did, for which he gave me a ſhilling:</hi> I <hi>offered the mony to my maſter, but he bade me keep it: and with it</hi> J <hi>bought a piece of Horſe fleſh.</hi> Afterwards he asked me to make a Cap for his boy, for which he invited me to Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. J went, and he gave me a Pancake, about as big as two fingers; it was made of parched wheat, beaten, and fryed in Bears greaſe, but <hi>I</hi> though <hi>I</hi> never taſted pleaſanter meat in my life. There was a <hi>Squaw</hi> who ſpake to me to make a ſhirt for her <hi>Sannup,</hi> for which ſhe gave me a piece of Bear. Another asked me to knit a pair of Stockins, for which ſhe gave me a quart of Peaſe: J boyled my Peaſe and Bear together, and invited my maſter and miſtriſs to dinner, but the proud Goſſip, be cauſe J ſerved them both in one Diſh, would eat nothing, except on bit that he gave her upon the point of his knife. Hearing that my ſon was come to this place, J went to ſee him, and found him lying flat upon the ground: J asked him how he could ſleep ſo? he anſwered me, <hi>That he was not aſleep, but at Prayer;</hi> and lay ſo that they might not obſerve what he was doing. J pray God he may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber theſe things now he is returned in ſafety. At
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192319:20"/>this Place (the Sun now getting higher) what with the beams and heat of the Sun, and the ſmoak of the <hi>Wigwams,</hi> J thought I ſhould have been blind, I could ſcarce diſcern one <hi>Wigwam</hi> from another, There was here one <hi>Mary Thurston</hi> of <hi>Medfield,</hi> who ſeeing how it was with me, lent me a Hat to wear: but as ſoon as I was gone, the <hi>Squaw</hi> who owned that <hi>Mary Thurſton</hi>) came running after me, and got it away again. <hi>Here was the</hi> Squaw <hi>that gave me one ſpoonfull of Meal.</hi> I put it in my Pocket to keep it ſafe: yet notwithſtanding ſome body ſtole it, but put five <hi>Indian</hi> Corns in the room of it: which Corns were the greateſt Proviſions J had in my travel for one day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Indians</hi> returning from <hi>North-Hamptom,</hi> brought with them ſome Horſes, and Sheep, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which they had taken: J deſired them, that they would carry me to <hi>Albany,</hi> upon one of thoſe Horſes, and ſell me for Powder: for ſo they had ſometimes diſcourſed. J was utterly hopleſs of getting home on foot, the way that I came. I could hardly bear to think of the many weary ſheps J had taken, to come to this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>The ninth Remove.</head>
               <p>But in ſtead of going either to <hi>Albany</hi> or home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, we muſt go five miles up the River, and then go over it. Here we abode a while. Here lived a ſorry <hi>Indian,</hi> who ſpoke to me to make him a ſhirt, when I had done it, he would pay we nothing. But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192319:20"/>he living by the River ſide, where I often went to ſetch water, <hi>I</hi> would often be putting of him in mind, and calling for my pay: at laſt he told me, if <hi>I</hi> would make another ſhirt, for a <hi>Papoos</hi> not yet born, he would give me a knife, which he did when I had done it. <hi>I</hi> carried the knife in, and my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter asked me to give it him, and I was not a little glad that I had any thing that they would accept of, and be pleaſed with. When we were at this place, my Maſters maid came home, ſhe had been gone <hi>three weeks</hi> into the <hi>Narrhaganſet Country,</hi> to fetch Corn, where they had ſtored up ſome in the ground: ſhe brought home about a peck and half of Corn. This was about the time that their great Captain, <hi>Naananto,</hi> was killed in the <hi>Narrhagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Countrey. My Son being now about a mile from me,</hi> I <hi>asked liberty to go and ſee him, they bade me go, and away I went: but quickly loſt my ſelf, travelling over Hills and thorough Swamps, and could not find the way to him.</hi> And I cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire at the wonderfull power and goodneſs of God to me, in that, though I was gone from home, and met with all ſorts of <hi>Indian,</hi> and thoſe I had no knowledge of, and there being no Chriſtian ſoul near me; yet not one of them offered the leaſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable miſcarriage to me. I turned homeward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and met with my maſter, he ſhewed me the way to my Son: When <hi>I</hi> came to him I found him not well; and withall he had a boyl on his ſide, which much troubled him: We bemoaned one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192319:21"/>while, as the Lord helped us, and then I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again. When I was returned, I found my ſelf as unſatisfied as I was before. I went up and down mourning and lamenting: and my ſpirit was ready to ſink, with the thoughts of my poor Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren: my Son was ill, and I could not but think of his mournfull looks, and no Chriſtian-Friend was near him, to do any office of love for him, either for Soul or Body. And my poor Girl, I knew not where ſhe was, nor whither ſhe was ſick, or well, or alive, or dead. J repaired under theſe thoughts to my Bible (my great comfort in that time) and that Scripture came to my hand, <hi>Caſt thy burden u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Lord, and He ſhall ſuſtain thee,</hi> Pſal. 55.22.</p>
               <p>But I was fain to go and look after ſomething to fatisfie my hunger, and going among the <hi>Wigwams,</hi> J went into one, and there found a <hi>Squaw</hi> who, ſhewed her ſelf very kind to me, and gave me a piece of Bear. J put it into my pocket, and came home, but could not find an opportunity to broil it, for fear they would get it from me, and there it lay all that day and night in my ſtinking pocket. In the morning J went to the ſame <hi>Squaw,</hi> who had a Kettle of Ground nuts boyling; J asked her to let me boyle my piece of Bear in her Kettle, which ſhe did, and gave me ſome Ground-nuts to eat with it: and J cannot but think how pleaſant it was to me. J have ſometime ſeen Bear bake very handſomly among the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſome liked it, but the thoughts that it was Bear, made me
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192319:21"/>tremble: but now that was ſavoury to me that one would think was enough to turn the ſtomacn of a bruit Creature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>One bitter cold day, j could find no room to ſit down before the fire: I went out, and could not tell what to do, but I went in to another</hi> Wigwam, <hi>where they were alſo ſitting round the fire, but the</hi> Squaw <hi>laid a skin for me, and bid me ſit down, and gave me ſome Ground-nuts, and bade me come again: and told me they would buy me, if they were able, and yet theſe were ſtrangers to me that I never ſaw before.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>The tenth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>That day a ſmall part of the Company removed about three quarters of a mile, intending further the next day.</hi> When they came to the place where they intended to lodge, and bad pitched their <hi>wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wams;</hi> being hungry J went again back to the place we were before at, to get ſomething to eat: being encouraged by the <hi>Squaws</hi> kindneſs, who bade me come again; when J was there, there came an <hi>Indian</hi> to look after me, who when he had found me, kickt me all along: J went home and found Veniſon roaſting that night, but they would not give me one bit of it. Sometimes J met with favour, and ſometimes with nothing but frowns.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>The eleventh Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next day in the morning they took their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, intending a dayes journey up the River, j took
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192319:22"/>my load at my back, and quickly we came to wade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the River: and paſſed over tireſome and we ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome hills.</hi> One hill was ſo ſteep that J was fain to creep up upon my knees, and to hold by the twiggs and buſhes to keep my ſelf from falling backward. My head alſo was ſo light, that J uſually reeled as J went; but J hope all theſe weariſome ſteps that j have taken, are but a forewarning of me to the heavenly reſt. I <hi>know, O Lord, that thy Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are right, and that thou in faithfulneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted me,</hi> Pſal. 119 71.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>The twelfth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was upon a Sabbath-day-morning, that they prepared for their Travel.</hi> This morning j asked my maſter whither he would ſell me to my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; he anſwered me <hi>Nux,</hi> which did much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce my ſpirit. My miſtriſs, before we went, was gone to the burial of a <hi>Papoos,</hi> and returning, ſhe found me ſitting and reading in my Bible; ſhe ſnatched it haſtily out of my hand, and threw it out of doors; I ran out and catcht it up, and put it into my pocket, and never let her ſee it afterward. Then they packed up their things to be gone, and gave me my load: I complained it was too heavy, whereupon ſhe gave me a ſlap in the face, and bade me go; I lifted up my heart to God, hoping that Redemption was not far off: and the rather becauſe their inſolency grew worſe and worſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the thoughts of my going homeward (for we bent our courſe) much cheared my Spirit, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192319:22"/>made my burden ſeem light, and almoſt nothing at all.</hi> But (to my amazment and great perplexity) the ſcale was ſoon turned: for when we had gone a little way, on a ſudden my miſtriſs gives out, ſhe would go no further, but turn back again, and ſaid. I muſt go back again with her, and ſhe called her <hi>Sannup,</hi> and would have had him gone back alſo, but he would not, but ſaid, <hi>He would go on, and come to us again in three dayes.</hi> My Spirit was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this, I confeſs, very impatient, and almoſt outragious. I thought <hi>I</hi> could as well have dyed as went back: I cannot declare the trouble that I was in about it; but yet back again I muſt go. As ſoon as I had an opportunity, <hi>I</hi> took my Bible to read, and that quieting Scripture came to my hand, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.10. <hi>Be still, and know that</hi> I <hi>am God.</hi> Which ſtilled my ſpirit for the preſent: But a ſore time of tryal, I concluded, J had to go through. My maſter being gone, who ſeemed to me the beſt, friend that I had of an <hi>Indian,</hi> both in cold and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and quickly ſo it proved. Down I ſat, with my heart as full as it could hold, and yet ſo hungry that I could not ſit neither: but going out to ſee what I could find, and walking among the Trees, I found ſix <hi>Acrons,</hi> and two <hi>Cheſ-nuts,</hi> which were ſome refreſhment to me. Towards Night I gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me ſome ſticks for my own comfort, that I might not ly a-cold: but when we came to ly down they bade me go out, and ly ſome-where-elſe, for they had company (they ſaid) come in more than
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192319:23"/>their own: <hi>I</hi> told them, I could not tell where to go, they bade me go look; I told them, if I went to another <hi>Wigwam</hi> they would be angry, and ſend m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> home again. Then one of the Company drew his ſword, and told me he would run me thorough if <hi>I</hi> did not go preſently. Then was <hi>I</hi> fain to ſtoop to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude fellow, and to go out in the night, J knew not whither. <hi>Mine eyes have ſeen that fellow afterwards walking up and down</hi> Boſton, <hi>under the appearance of a</hi> Friend-Indian, <hi>and ſeverall others of the like Cut.</hi> I went to one <hi>Wigwam,</hi> and they told me they had no room. Then I went to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they ſaid the ſame; at laſt an old <hi>Indian</hi> bade me come to him, and his <hi>Squaw</hi> give me ſome Ground-nuts; ſhe gave me alſo ſomething to lay under my head, and a good fire we had: and through the good providence of God, I had a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable lodging that night. In the morning, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Indian</hi> bade me come at night, and he would give me ſix Ground nuts, which I did. We were at this place and time about two miles from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necticut River.</hi> We went in the morning to gather Ground nuts, to the River, and went back again that night. <hi>I</hi> went with a good load at my back for they when they went, though but a little way, would carry all their trumpery with them) I told them the skin was off my back, but J had no other comforting anſwer from them than this, <hi>That i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would be no matter if myhead were off too.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:192319:23"/>
               <head>The thirteenth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtead of going toward the</hi> Bay, <hi>which was that</hi> I <hi>deſired,</hi> I <hi>muſt go with them five or ſix miles down the River into a mighty Thicket of Bruſh: where we abode almoſt a fortnight.</hi> Here one asked me to make a ſhirt for her <hi>Papoos,</hi> for which ſhe gave me a meſs of Broth, which was thickened with meal made of the Bark of a Tree, and to make it the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſhe had put into it about a handfull of Peaſe, and a ſew roaſted Ground-nuts, J had not ſeen my ſon a pritty while, and here was an <hi>Indian</hi> of whom J made inquiry after him, and asked him when he ſaw him: he anſwered me, that ſuch a time his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter roaſted him, and that himſelf did eat a piece of him, as big as his two fingers, and that he was very good meat: <hi>But the Lord upheld my Spirit, under this diſcouragement; and I conſidered their horrible addictedneſs to lying, and that there is not one of them that makes the least conſcience of ſpeaking of truth.</hi> In this place, on a cold night, as I lay by the fire, J removed a ſtick that kept the heat from me, a <hi>Squaw</hi> moved it down again, at which I lookt up, and ſhe threw a handfull of aſhes in mine eyes; J thought J ſhould have been quite blinded, and have never ſeen more: but lying down, the water run out of my eyes, and carried the dirt with it, that by the morning, I recovered my ſight again. Yet upon this, and the like occaſions, I hope it is not too much to ſay with <hi>Job, Have pitty upon me, have pitty upon me, O ye my Friends, for the Hand
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192319:24"/>of the Lord has touched me.</hi> And here I cannot but remember how many times ſitting in their <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wams,</hi> and muſing on things paſt, I ſhould ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leap up and run out, as if I had been at home, forgetting where I was, and what my condition was: But when I was without, and ſaw nothing but <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and <hi>Woods,</hi> and a company of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous heathens: my mind quickly returned to me, which made me think of that, ſpoken concerning <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who ſaid, I <hi>will go out and ſhake myſelf as at other times, but he wiſt not that the Lord was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him.</hi> About this time I began to think that all my hopes of Reſtoration would come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>I</hi> thought of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, and hoped for their coming, and being taken by them, but that failed. <hi>I</hi> hoped to be carried to <hi>Albany,</hi> at the <hi>Indians</hi> had diſcourſed before, but that failed alſo. I thought of being ſold to my Husband, as my maſter ſpake, but in ſtead of that, my maſter himſelf was gone, and j left behind, ſo that my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was now quite réady to ſink. J asked them to let me go out and pick up ſome ſticks, that j might get alone, <hi>And poure out my heart unto the Lord.</hi> Then alſo j took my Bible to read, but j found no comfort here neither: which many times j was went to find: <hi>So eaſie a thing it is with God to dry up the Streames of Scripture-comfort from us.</hi> Yet j can ſay, that in all my ſorrows and afflictions, God did not leave me to have my impatience work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelf, as if his wayes were unrighteous.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192319:24"/>
                  <hi>But I knew that he laid upon me leſs then j deſerved</hi> Afterward, before this dolefull time ended with me, I was turning the leaves of my Bible, and the Lord brought to me ſome Scriptures, which did a little revive me, as that <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.8 <hi>For my thoughts are not your thougts, neither are your wayes my ways ſaith the Lord.</hi> And alſo that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord, truſt alſo in him, and he ſhal bring it to paſs.</hi> About this time they came yelping from <hi>Hadly,</hi> where they had killed three <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> and brought one Captive with them, <hi>viz. Thomas Read.</hi> They all gathered about the poor Man, asking him many Queſtions. I deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-alſo to go and ſee him; and when I came, he was crying bitterly: ſuppoſing they would quickly kill him. Whereupon j asked one of them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they intended to kill him; he anſwered me, they would not: He being a little cheared with that, I asked him about the wel-fare of my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thand, he told me he ſaw him ſuch a time in the <hi>Bay,</hi> and he was well, but very melancholly. By which I certainly underſtood <hi>(though I ſuſpected it before)</hi> that whatſoever the <hi>Indians</hi> told me reſpecting him was vanity and lies. Some of them told me, he was dead, and they had killed him: ſome ſaid he was Married again, and that the Governour wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to Marry; and told him he ſhould have his choice, and that all perſwaded I was dead. So like were theſe barbarous creatures to him who was a lyar from the beginning.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:192319:25"/>
               <p>As I was ſitting once in the <hi>Wigwam</hi> here, <hi>Phillps</hi> Maid came in with the Child in her arms, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to give het a piece of my Apron, to make a flap for it, I told her I would not: then my Miſt: riſs bad me give it, but ſtill I ſaid no: the maid told me if I would not give her a piece, ſhe would tear a piece off it: <hi>I</hi> told her I would tear her Coat then with that my Miſtriſs riſes up, and takes up a ſtick big enough to have killed me, and ſtruck at me with it, but J ſtept out, and ſhe ſtruck the ſtick into the Mat of the Wigwam. But while ſhe was pull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it out, j ran to the Maid and gave her all my Apron, and ſo that ſtorm went over.</p>
               <p>Hearing that my Son was come to this place, I went to ſee him, and told him his Father was well, but very melancholly: he told me he was as much grieved for his Father as for himſelf; I wondred at his ſpeech, for I thought I had enough upon my ſpirit in reference to my ſelf, to make me mindleſs of my Husband and every one elſe: they being ſafe among their Friends. He told me alſo, that a while before, his Maſter (together with other <hi>Indians</hi>) where going to the <hi>French</hi> for Powder; but by the way the <hi>Mohawks</hi> met with them, and killed four of their Company which made the reſt turn back again, for which I deſire that myſelf and he may bleſs the Lord; for it might have been worſe with him, had he been ſold to the <hi>French,</hi> than it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be in his remaining with the <hi>Indians</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I went to ſee an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Youth in this place, one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:192319:25"/>
                  <hi>John Gilberd</hi> of <hi>Spring field</hi> J found him lying without dores, upon to ground; j asked him how he did? he told me he was very ſick of a flux, with eating ſo much blood: They had turned him out of the Wigwam, and with him an <hi>indian Papoos,</hi> almoſt dead, (whoſe Parents had been killed) in a bitter cold day, without fire or clothes: the young man himſelf had nothing on, but his ſhirt &amp; waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat. This ſight was enough to melt a heart of flint. There they lay quivering in the Cold, the youth round like a dog; the <hi>Papoos</hi> ſtretcht out, with his eyes and noſe and mouth full of dirt, and yet alive, and groaning. j adviſed John to go and get to ſome fire: he told me he could not ſtand, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perſwaded him ſtill, left he ſhouldly there and die: and with much adoe j got him to a fire, and went my ſelf home. As ſoon as j was got home, his Maſters Daughter came after me, to know what j had done with the <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> j told her j had got him to a fire in ſuch a place. Now had j need to pray <hi>Pauls</hi> Prayer, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.2. <hi>That we may be delivered from unreaſonable and wicked men.</hi> For her ſatisfaction j went along with her, and brought her to him; but before j got home again, it was noiſed about, that j was running away and getting the <hi>Engliſh</hi> youth: along with me: that as ſoon as I came in, they began to rant and domineer: asking me where j had been, and what j had been doing? and ſaying they would knock him on the head: I told them, j had been ſeeing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192319:26"/>the <hi>Engliſh Youth,</hi> and that I would not run away, they told me I lyed, and taking up a Hatchet, they came to me, and ſaid they would knock me down if I ſtirred out again; and ſo confined me to the <hi>Wigwam.</hi> Now may J ſay with <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.14. I <hi>am in a great ſtrait.</hi> If I keep in, I muſt dy with hunger, and if <hi>I</hi> go out, <hi>I</hi> muſt be knockt in head. This diſtreſſed condition held that day, and half the next; <hi>And then the Lord remembred me, whoſe mercyes are great.</hi> Then came an <hi>Indian</hi> to me with a pair of ſtockings that were too big for him, and he would have me ravel them out, and knit them fit for him. I ſhewed my ſelf willing, and bid him ask my miſtriſs if <hi>I</hi> might go along with him a little way; ſhe ſaid yes, J might, but J was not a little refreſht with that news, that J had my liberty again. Then J went along with him, and he gave me ſome roaſted Ground-nuts, which did again revive my feeble ſtomach.</p>
               <p>Being got out of her ſight: J had time and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty again to look into my Bible: <hi>Which was my Guid by day, and my Pillow by night.</hi> Now that comfortable Scripture preſonted it ſelf to me, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7. <hi>For a ſmal moment have I forſaken thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but with great mercies will I gather thee.</hi> Thus the Lord car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me along from one time to another, and made good to me this precious promiſe, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Then my Son came to ſee me,</hi> and J asked his maſter to <hi>let</hi> him ſtay a while with me, that J
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192319:26"/>might comb his head, and look over him, for he was almoſt over come with lice. He told me, when <hi>I</hi> had done, that he was very hungry, but I had nothing to relieve him; but bid him go into the Wigwams as he went along, and ſee if he could get any thing among them. Which he did, and it ſeemes tarried a little too long; for his Maſter was angry with him, and beat him, and then ſold him. Then he came running to tell me he had a new Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. and that he had given him ſome Groundouts already. Then <hi>I</hi> went along with him to his new Maſter who told me he loved him: and he ſhould not want. So his Maſter carried him away, &amp; j never ſaw him afterward. till j ſaw him at <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cataqua</hi> in <hi>Portsmouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That night they bade me go out of the <hi>Wigwam</hi> again: my Miſtriſſes Papoos was ſick, and it died that night, and there was one benefit in it, that there was more room. J went to a <hi>Wigwam,</hi> and they bade me come in, and gave me a skin to ly upon, and a meſs of Venſon and Ground-nuts, which was a choice Diſh among them. On the morrow they burried the <hi>Papoos,</hi> and afterward, both morning and evening, there came a company to mourn and howle with her: though j confeſs, j could not much condole with them. Many ſorrowfull dayes j had in this place: often getting alone; <hi>like a Crane, or a Swallow ſo did I chatter: I did mourn as a Dove, mine eyes fail with looking upward Oh, Lord j am oppreſſed, undertake for me,</hi> Iſa. 38 14
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192319:27"/>I could tell the Lord as <hi>Hezeakiah,</hi> ver. 3. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber now O Lord,</hi> I <hi>beſeech thee, kow</hi> I <hi>have walked before thee in truth.</hi> Now had <hi>I</hi> time to examine al my wayes: my Conſcience did not accuſe me of un-righteouſneſs toward one or other: yet <hi>I</hi> ſaw how in m y walk with God, I had been a careleſs creature. As <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have</hi> I <hi>ſinned:</hi> &amp; I might ſay with the poor Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, <hi>God be mereiful unto me a ſinner.</hi> On the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-dayes, I could look upon the Sun and think how People were going to the houſe of God, to have their Souls refreſht; &amp; then home, and their bodies alſo: but I was deſtitute of both; &amp; might ſay as the poor Prodigal, <hi>he would fain have filled his belly with the husks that the Swine did eat, and no man gave unto him,</hi> Luke 15.16 For <hi>I</hi> muſt ſay with him, <hi>Father I have ſinned againſt Heaven, and in thy ſight,</hi> ver 21. <hi>I</hi> remembred how on the night before &amp; after the Sabbath, when my Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was about me, and Relations and Neighbours with us, we could pray and ſing, and then refreſh our bodies with the good creatures of God; and then have a comfortable Bed to ly down on: but in ſtead of all this, <hi>I</hi> had only a little Swill for the body, and then like a Swine, muſt ly down on the ground. I cannot expreſs to man the ſorrow that lay upon my Spirit, the Lord knows it. Yet that comfortable Scripture would often come to my mind, <hi>For a ſmall moment have</hi> I <hi>forſaken thee, but with great mercies will I gather thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192319:27"/>
               <head>The fourteenth Remove.</head>
               <p>Now muſt we pack up and be gone from this Thicket, bending our courſe toward the Bay-towns I haveing nothing to eat by the way this day, but a few crumbs of Cake, that an <hi>Indian</hi> gave my girle the ſame day we were taken. She gave it me, and I put it in my pocket: there it lay, till it was ſo mouldy (for want of good baking) that one could not tell what it was made of; it fell all to crumbs, &amp; grew ſo dry and hard, that it was like little flints; &amp; this refreſhed me many times, when I was ready to faint. It was in my thoughts when I put it into my mouth; that if ever I return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I would tell the World what a bleſſing the Lord gave to ſuch mean ſood. As we went along, they killed a <hi>Deer,</hi> with a young one in her, they gave me a piece of the <hi>Fawn,</hi> and it was ſo young and tender, that one might eat the bones as well as the fleſh, and yet I thought it very good. When night came on we ſate down; it rained, but they quickly got up a Bark Wigwam, where I lay dry that night. I looked out in the morning, and many of them had line in the rain all night, I ſaw by their Reaking. Thus the Lord dealt mercifully with me many times, and I fared, better than many of them. In the morning they took the blood of the <hi>Deer,</hi> and put it into the Paunch, and ſo boyled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I could eat nothing of that, though they ate it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tly. And yet they were ſo nice in other things,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192319:28"/>that when I had fetcht water, and had put the Diſh I dipt the water with, into the Kettle of water which I brought, they would ſay, they would knock me down; for they ſaid, it was a ſluttiſh trick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>The fifteenth Remove.</head>
               <p>We went on our Travel. I having got one handfull of Ground-nuts, for my ſupport that day they gave me my load, and j went on cheerfully [with the thoughts of going homeward] haveing my burden more on my back than my ſpirit: we came to <hi>Baquang River</hi> again that day, near which we abode a few dayes Sometimes one of them would give me a Pipe, another a little Tobacco, another a little Salt: which I would change for a little Victuals. I cannot but think what a Wolviſh appetite perſons have in a ſtarving condition: for many times when they gave me that which was hot, I was ſo greedy, that I ſhould burn my mouth, that it would trouble me hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet I ſhould quickly do the ſame again. And after I was thorougly hungry, <hi>I</hi> was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſatisfied. For though ſometimes it fell out, that <hi>I</hi> got enough, and did eat till I could eat no more, yet I was as unſatisfied as J was when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. And now could J ſee that Scripture verified (there being many Scriptures which we do not take notice of, or underſtand till we are affli&amp;ed) <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Thou ſhalt eat and not be ſatisfied.</hi> Now might I ſee more than ever before, the miſeries that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192319:28"/>ſin hath brought upon us: Many times I ſhould be ready to run out againſt the Heathen, but the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture would quiet me again, <hi>Amos,</hi> 3 6. <hi>Shal there be evil in the City, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> The Lord help me to make a right improvment of His Word, and that I might learn that great leſſon, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8, 9. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee (Oh Man) what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do justly, and love mercy, and walk humbly with thy God? Hear ye the rod, and who hath appointed it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>The ſixteenth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We began this Remove with wading over</hi> Baquag <hi>River: the water was up to the knees, and the ſtream very ſwift, and ſo cold that I thought it would have cut me in ſunder.</hi> j was ſo weak and ſeeble, that j reeled as I went along, and thought there I muſt end my dayes at laſt, after my bearing and getting thorough ſo many difficulties; the <hi>Indians</hi> ſtood laughing to ſee me ſtaggering along: but in my diſtreſs the Lord gave me experience of the truth, and goodneſs of that promiſe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorough the Waters,</hi> I <hi>will be with thee, and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee.</hi> Then I ſat down to put on my ſtockins and ſhoos, with the teares running down mine eyes, and many ſorrowfull thoughts in my heart, but I gat up to go along with them. Quickly there came up to us an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> who informed them, that I muſt go to <hi>Wachu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> to my maſter, for there was a Letter come from
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192319:29"/>the Council to the <hi>Saggamores,</hi> about redeeming the Captives, and that there would be another in fourteen dayes, and that I muſt be there ready. My heart was ſo heavy before that I could ſcarce ſpeak or go in the path; and yet now ſo light, that J could run. My ſtrength ſeemed to come again, and recruit my feeble knees, and aking heart: yet it pleaſed them to go but one mile that night, and there we ſtayed two dayes. In that time came a company of <hi>Indians</hi> to us, near thirty, all on horſe-back. My heart skipt within me, thinking they had been <hi>Engliſh men</hi> at the firſt ſigbt of them, for they were dreſſed in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Apparel, with Hats, white Neckcloths,, and Saſhes about their waſts, and Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds upon their ſhoulders: but when they came near, their was a vaft difference between the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faces of Chriſtians, and the foul looks of thoſe Heathens, which much damped my ſpirit again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>The ſeventeenth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A comfortable Remove it was to me, becauſe of my hopes.</hi> They gave me a pack, and along we went chearfully; but quickly my will proved more than my ſtrength; having little or no refreſhing my ſtrength failed me, and my ſpirit were almoſt quite gone. Now may I ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. I 19.22, 23, 24. I <hi>am poor and needy, and my heart is wounded within me.</hi> I <hi>am gone like the ſhadow when it dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ineth:</hi> I <hi>am toſſed up and down like the locuſts: my knees are weak through faſting, and my fliſh fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192319:29"/>offaineſs.</hi> At night we came to an <hi>Indian Town,</hi> and the <hi>Indians</hi> ſate down by a <hi>Wigwam</hi> diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but J was almoſt ſpent, and could ſcarce ſpeak. I laid down my load, and went into the <hi>Wigwam,</hi> and there ſat an <hi>Indian</hi> boyling of <hi>Horſes feet</hi> (they being wont to eat the fleſh firſt, and when the feet were old and dried, and they had nothing elſe, they would cut off the feet and uſe them) I asked him to give me a little of his Broth, or Water they were boiling in; he took a diſh, and gave me one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Samp, and bid me take as much of the Broth as I would. Then <hi>I</hi> put ſome of the hot water to the Samp, and drank it up, and my ſpirit came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. He gave me alſo a piece of the Ruff or Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſmall Guts, and I broiled it on the coals; and now may I ſay with <hi>Jonathan, See,</hi> I <hi>pray you, how mine eyes have been enlightened, becauſe j taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little of this honey,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.29. Now is my Spirit revived again, though means be never ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, yet if the Lord beſtow his bleſſing u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, they ſhall refreſh both Soul and Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>The eighteenth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We took up our packs and along we went, but a weariſome day</hi> I <hi>had of it.</hi> As we went along I ſaw an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> ſtript naked, and lying dead upon the ground, but knew not who it was. Then we came to another <hi>Indian Town,</hi> where we ſtayed all night. In this Town there were four <hi>Engliſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Captives; and one of them my own Siſters.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192319:30"/>I went to ſee how ſhe did, and ſhe was well, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering her Captive-condition. I would have tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried that night with her, but they that owned her would not ſuffer it. Then I went into another <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wam,</hi> where they were boyling Corn and Beant, which was alovely ſight to ſee, but J could not get a taſte thereof. Then I went to another <hi>Wigwam,</hi> where there were two of the <hi>Engliſh Children;</hi> the <hi>Squaw</hi> was boyling <hi>Horſes feet,</hi> then ſhe cut me off a little piece, and gave one of the <hi>Engliſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> a piece alſo. Being very hungry I had quickly eat up mine, but the Child could not bite it, it was ſo tough and ſinewy, but lay ſucking, gnawing, chewing and ſlabbering of it in the moutb and band, then I took it of the Child, and eat it my ſelf, and favoury it was to my taſte. Then I may ſay as <hi>Job Chap.</hi> 6.7. <hi>The things that my ſoul refuſed to touch, are as my ſorrowfull meat.</hi> Thus the Lord made that pleaſant refreſhing, which another time would have been an abomination. Then I went home to my miſtreſſes <hi>Wigwam;</hi> and they told me <hi>I</hi> diſgraced my maſter with begging, and if I did ſo any more, they would knock me in head: I told them, they had as good knock me in head as ſtarve me to death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>The ninteenth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>They ſaid, when we went out, that we muſt travel to</hi> Wachuſet <hi>this day.</hi> But a bitter weary day I had of it, travelling now three dayes to gether, without reſting any day between. At laſt, after many wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:192319:30"/>ſteps, <hi>I</hi> ſaw <hi>Wachuſet</hi> hills, but many miles off. Then we came to a great <hi>Swamp,</hi> through which we travelled up to the knees, in mud and water, which was heavy going to one tyred before. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt ſpent, <hi>I</hi> thought I ſhould have ſunk down at laſt, and never gat out; but <hi>I</hi> may ſay, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.18. <hi>When my foot ſlipped, thy mercy, O Lord held me up.</hi> Going along, having indeed my life, but little ſpirit, <hi>Philip,</hi> who was in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, came up and took me by the hand, and ſaid, <hi>Two weeks more and you ſhal be Miſtreſs again. I</hi> asked him, if he ſpake true? he anſwered, Yes, <hi>and quickly you ſhal come to your maſter again;</hi> who had been gone from us three weeks. After many weary ſteps we came to <hi>Wachuſet,</hi> where he was: and glad I was to ſee him. He asked me, <hi>When</hi> J <hi>waſht me?</hi> J told him not this month, then he fetcht me ſome water himſelf, and bid me waſh, and gave me the Glaſs to ſee how j lookt; and bid his <hi>Squaw</hi> give me ſomething to eat: ſo ſhe gave me a meſs of Beans and meat, and a little Ground-nut Cake. <hi>I</hi> was wonderfully revived with this favour ſhewed me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.46 <hi>He made them alſo to be pittied, of all thoſe that carried them Captives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My maſter had three</hi> Squaws, <hi>living ſometimes with one, and ſometimes with another one, this old</hi> Squaw, <hi>at whoſe</hi> Wigwan <hi>j was, and with whom my Master had been thoſe three weeks.</hi> Another was <hi>Wettimore,</hi> with whom I had lived and ſerved all this while: A ſevere and proud Dame ſhe was;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:192319:31"/>beſtowing every day in dreſſing her ſelf neat as much time as any of the Gentry of the land: pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering her hair, and painting her face, going with Neck-laces, with Jewels in her ears, and Bracelets upon her hands: When ſhe had dreſſed her ſelf, her work was to make Girdles of <hi>Wampom</hi> and <hi>Biads.</hi> The third <hi>Squaw</hi> was a younger one, by whom he had two <hi>Papooſes.</hi> By that time I was refreſht by the old <hi>Squaw,</hi> with whom my maſter was, <hi>Wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timores</hi> Maid came to call me home, at which I fell a weeping. Then the old <hi>Squaw</hi> told me, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me, that if I wanted victuals, j ſhould come to her, and that j ſhouldly there in her <hi>Wigwam.</hi> Then j went with the maid, and quickly came again and lodged there. The <hi>Squaw</hi> laid a Mat under me, and a good Rugg over me; the firſt time J had any ſuch kindneſs ſhowed me. J underſtood that <hi>Wettimore</hi> thought, that if ſhe ſhould let me go and ſerve with the old <hi>Squaw,</hi> ſhe would be in danger to looſe, not only my ſervice, but the redemption<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay alſo. And j was not a little glad to hear this; being by it raiſed in my hopes, that in Gods due time there would be an end of this ſorrowfull hour. Then came an <hi>Indians</hi> and asked me to knit him three pair of Stockins, for which j had a Hat, and a ſilk handkerchief. Then another asked me to mak her a ſhift, for which ſhe gave me an Apron.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then came</hi> Tom <hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>with the ſecond Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Council, about the Captives.</hi> Though they were <hi>Indians,</hi> j gat them by the hand, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192319:31"/>burſt out into tears; my heart was ſo full that J could not ſpeak to them; but recovering my ſelf, j asked them how my husband did, &amp; all my friends and acquainiance? they ſaid, <hi>They are all very well but melancohly.</hi> They brought me two Biskets, and a pound of Tobacco. The Tobacco j quickly gave away; when it was all gone, one asked me to give him a pipe of Tobacco, I told him it was all gone; <hi>then began be to rant and threaten.</hi> I told him when my Husband camel would give him ſome: <hi>Hang him Rogne (ſayes be)</hi> I <hi>will knock out his brains, if he comes here.</hi> And then again, in the ſame breath they would ſay, <hi>That if there ſhould come an hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred without Guns, they would do them no hurt.</hi> So unſtable and like mad men they were. So that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worſt, I durſt not ſend to my Husband, though there were ſome thoughts of his coming to Redeem and ſetch me, not knowing what might follow; <hi>For there was little more truſt to them then to the maſter they ſerved.</hi> When the Letter was come, the <hi>Saggamores</hi> met to conſult about the Captives, and called me to them to enquire how much my husband would give to redeem me, when I came I ſate down among them, as J was wont to do, as their manner is: <hi>Then they bade me ſtand up,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>they were the General Court. They bid me ſpeak what I thought he would give,</hi> Now knowing that all we had was deſtroyed by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> I was in a great ſtrait: I thought if I ſhould ſpeak of but a little, it would be ſlighted, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192319:32"/>the matter; if of a great ſum, I knew not where is would be procured: yet at a venture, I ſaid <hi>Twenty pounds,</hi> yet deſired them to take leſs; but they would not hear of that, but ſent that meſſage to <hi>Boſton,</hi> that for <hi>Twenty pound.</hi> I ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed. It was a Praying-<hi>Indian</hi> that wrote their Letter for them. There was another Praying <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> who told me, that he had a brother, that would not eat Horſe; his conſcience was ſo tender and ſcrupulous (though as large as hell, forthe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtruction of poor <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) Then he ſaid, he read that Scripture to him, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 6.25. <hi>There was a ſamine in</hi> Samatia, <hi>and behold they beſieged it, untill an Aſſes head was ſold for fourſcore pieces of ſilver, and the fourth part of a Kab of Doves dung, for five pieces of ſilver.</hi> He expounded this place to his brother, and ſhewed him that it was lawfull to eat that in a Famine which is not at another time. And now, ſayes he, he will eat Horſe with any <hi>Indian of them all.</hi> There was another Praying-<hi>Indian,</hi> who when he bad done all the miſchief that he could, betrayed his own Father into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands, thereby to purchaſe his own life. Another Praying-<hi>Indian</hi> was at <hi>Sudbury-fight,</hi> though, as he deſerved, he was afterward hanged for it, There was another Praying <hi>Indian,</hi> ſo wicked and cruel, as to wear a ſtring about his neck, ſtrung with <hi>Chriſtians</hi> fingers. Another Praying-<hi>Indian,</hi> when they went to <hi>Sudbury-fight,</hi> went with them, and his <hi>Squaw</hi> alſo with him, with her <hi>Papoos</hi> at her
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192319:32"/>back: Before they went to that fight, they got a company together to <hi>Powaw;</hi> the manner was as followeth. There was one that kneeled upon a <hi>Deer-skin,</hi> with the company round him in a ring who kneeled, and ſtriking upon the ground with their hands, and with ſticks; and muttering or humming with their mouths, beſides him who kneeled in the ring, there alſo ſtood one with a Gun in his hand: Then he one the <hi>Deer-skin</hi> made a ſpeech, and all manifeſted aſſent to it: and ſo they did many times together. Then they bade him with the Gun go out of the ring, which he did, but when he was out, they called him in again; but he ſeemed to make a ſtand, then they called the more earneſtly, till he returned again: Then they all ſang. Then they gave him two Guns, in either hand one: And ſo he on the <hi>Deer-skin</hi> began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and at the end of every ſentence in his ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they all aſſented, humming or muttering with their mouthes, and ſtriking upon the ground with their hands. Then they bade him with the two Guns go out of the ring again; which he did, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle way. Then they called him in again, but he made a ſtand; ſo they called him with greater ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs; but he ſtood reeling and wavering as if he knew not whither he ſhould ſtand or fall, or which way to go. Then they called him with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great vehemency, all of them, one and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: after a little while he turned in, ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he went, with his Armes ſtretched out, in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:192319:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>either hand a Gun. As ſoon as he came in, they all ſang and rejoyced exceedingly a while. And then he opened the <hi>Deer-skin,</hi> made another ſpeech unto which they all aſſented in a rejoicing manner: and ſo they ended their buſineſs, and forthwith went to <hi>Sudbury fight.</hi> To my thinking they went without any ſcruple, but that they ſhould proſper, and gain the victory: And they went out not ſo rejoycing, but they came home with as great a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. For they ſaid they had killed two Captains, and almoſt an hundred men. One <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> they brought along with them: and he ſaid, it was too true, for they had made ſad work at <hi>Sudbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> as indeed it proved. Yet they came home with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that rejoycing and triumphing over their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, which they were wont to ſhew at other times: but rather like Dogs (as they ſay) which have loſt their cars. Yet I could not pereceive that it was for their own loſs of men: They ſaid, they had not loſt above five or ſix: and I miſſed none, excep in one <hi>Wigwam.</hi> When they went, they acted as if the Devil had told them that they ſhould gain the victory: and now they acted, as if the Devil had told them they ſhould have a fall. Whither it were ſo or no, I cannot tell, but ſo it proved, for quickly they began to fall, and ſo held on that Summer, till they came to utter ruine. They came home on a Sabbath day, and the <hi>Powaw</hi> that kneeled upon the <hi>Deer-skin</hi> came home (I may ſay, without abule) as black as the Devil.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:192319:33"/>When my maſter came home, be came to me and bid me make a ſhirt for his <hi>Papoos,</hi> of a holland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced Pillowbeer. About that time there came an <hi>Indian</hi> to me and bid me come to his <hi>Wigwam,</hi> at night, and he would give me ſome Pork &amp; Ground nuts. Which I did, and as I was eating, another <hi>Indian</hi> ſaid to me, he ſeems to be your good Friend, but he killed two <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> at <hi>Sudbury,</hi> and there ly their Cloaths behind you: I looked behind me, and there I ſaw bloody Cloaths, with Bullet holes in them; yet the Lord ſuffered not this wretch to do me any hurt; Yea, inſtead of that, he many times refreſht me: five or ſix times did he and his <hi>Squaw</hi> refreſh my feeble carcaſs. If J went to their <hi>Wigwam</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any time, they would alwayes give me ſomething, and yet they were ſtrangers that I never ſaw before. Another <hi>Squaw</hi> gave me a piece of freſh Pork, and a little Salt with it, and lent me her Panto Fry it in; and I cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what a ſweet, pleaſant and delightfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh that bit had to me, to this day. So little do we prize common mercies when we have them to the full.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>The twentieth Remove.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was their uſual manner to remove, when they bad done any miſchief, leſt they ſhould be found out: and ſo they did at this time.</hi> We went about three or four miles, and there they built a great <hi>Wigwam,</hi> big enough to hold an hundred <hi>Indians,</hi> which they did in preparation to a great day of Dancing.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:192319:34"/>They would ſay now amongſt themſelves, that the <hi>Governour</hi> would be ſo angry for his loſs at <hi>Sudbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> that he would ſend no more about the Captives, which made me grieve and tremble. My Siſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſar from the place where we now were: and hearing that I was here, deſired her maſter to let her come and ſee me, and he was willing to it, and would go with her: but ſhe being ready before him, told him ſhe wonld go before, and was come within a Mile or two of the place; Then he overtook her, and began to rant as if he had been mad; and made her go back again in the Rain; ſo that I never ſaw her till j ſaw her in <hi>Charlestown.</hi> But the Lord requited many of their ill doings, for this <hi>Indian</hi> her Maſter, was hanged afterward at <hi>Boſton.</hi> The <hi>Indians</hi> now began to come from all quarters, againſt their merry dancing day. Among ſome of them came one <hi>Good wife Kettle:</hi> I told her my heart was ſo heavy that it was ready to break: ſo is mine too ſaid ſhe, but yet ſaid, I hope we ſhall hear ſome good news ſhortly. I could hear how earneſtly my Siſter deſired to ſee me, &amp; I as earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired to ſee her: and yet neither of us could get an opportunity. My Daughter was alſo now about a mile off, and I had not ſeen her in nine or ten weeks, as I had not ſeen my Siſter ſince our firſt taking. I earneſtly deſired them to let me go and ſee them: yea, I intreated, begged, and perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, but to let me ſee my Daughter; and yet ſo hard hearred were they, that they would not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:192319:34"/>ſuffer it. They made uſe of their tyrannical power whilſt they had it: but through the Lords wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mercy, their time was now but ſhort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>On a Sabbath day, the Sun being about an hour high in the afternoon; came Mr.</hi> John Hoar (<hi>the Council permitting him, and his own foreward ſpirit inclining him) together with the two forementioned</hi> Indians, Tom <hi>and</hi> Peter <hi>with their third Letter from the Council</hi> When they came near, I was abroad. though I ſaw them not, they preſently called me in, and bade me ſit down and not ſtir. Then they catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up their Guns, and away they ran, as if an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had been at hand; and the Guns went off apace I manifeſted ſome great trouble, and they asked me what was the matter? I told them, I <hi>thought they had killed the</hi> Engliſh-man (for they had in the mean time informed me that an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> was come) they ſaid, <hi>No;</hi> They ſhot over his Horſe and under, and before his Horſe; and they puſht him this way and that way, at their pleaſure: ſhewing what they conld do: Then they let them come to their <hi>Wigwams.</hi> I begged of them to let me ſee the <hi>Engliſh man,</hi> but they would not. But there was I fain to ſit their pleaſure. When they had talked their fill with him, they ſuffered me to go to him. We asked each other of our welfare, and how my Husband did, and all my Friends? He told me they were all well, and would be glad to ſee me. Amongſt other things which my Husband ſent me, there came a pound of <hi>Tobacco:</hi> which I ſold for nine ſhillings in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192319:35"/>Money: for many of the <hi>Indians</hi> for want of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco,</hi> ſmoaked <hi>Hemlock,</hi> and <hi>Ground-Ivy.</hi> it was a great miſtake in any, who thought I ſent for <hi>Tobacco:</hi> for through the ſavour of God, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire was overcome. I now asked them, whither I ſhould go home with Mr. <hi>Hoar?</hi> They anſwered <hi>No,</hi> one and another of them: and it being night, we lay down with that anſwer; in the morning, Mr <hi>Hoar</hi> invited the <hi>Saggamores</hi> to Dinner; but when we went to get it ready, we fond that they had ſtollen the greateſt part of the Proviſion Mr. <hi>Hoar</hi> had brought, our of his Bags, in the night: <hi>And we may ſee the wonderfull power of God, in that one paſſage, in that when there was ſuch a great number of the</hi> Indians <hi>together, and ſo greedy of a little good food; and no</hi> Engliſh <hi>there, but Mr. Hoar and my ſelf: that there they did not knock us in the bead, and take what we had: there being not only ſome Proviſion, but alſo Trading-cloth, a part of the twenty pounds agreed upon: But inſtead of doing us any miſchief, they ſeemed to be aſhamed of the fact, and ſaid, it were ſome</hi> Matchit Indian <hi>that did it.</hi> Oh, that we could believe that there is no thing too hard for God! God ſhewed his Power over the Heathen in this, <hi>as he did ever the hungry Lyons when</hi> Daniel <hi>was caſt into the Den.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hoar</hi> called them betime to Dinner, but they are very little, they being ſo buſie in dreſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and getting ready for their Dance: which was carried one by eight of them; four <hi>Men</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192319:35"/>four <hi>Squaws:</hi> My maſter and miſtriſs being two. He was dreſſed in his Holland ſhirt, with great Laces ſewed at the cail of it, he had his ſilver But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, his white Stockins, his Garters were hung round with Shillings, and he had Girdles of <hi>Wam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pom upon his head and ſhoulders.</hi> She had a Kerſey Coat, and covered with Girdles of <hi>Wampom</hi> from the Loins upward: her armes from her elbows to her hands were covered with Bracelets; there were handfulls of Neck-laces about her neck, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſorts of Jewels in her ears. She had fine red Stokins, and white Shoos, her hair powdered and face painted Red, that was alwayes before Black. And all the Dancers were after the ſame manner. There were two other ſinging and knocking on a Kettle for their muſick. They keept hopping up and down one after another, with a Kettle of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the midſt, ſtanding warm upon ſome Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to drink of when they were dry. They held on till it was almoſt night, throwing out <hi>Wampom</hi> to the ſtanders by. At night I asked them again, if I ſhould go home? They all as one ſaid No, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my Husband would come for me. When we were lain down, my Maſter went out of the <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wam,</hi> and by and by ſent in an <hi>Indian</hi> called <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Printer,</hi> who told Mr. <hi>Hoar,</hi> that my Maſter would let me go home to morrow, if he would let him have one pint of Liquors. Then Mr. <hi>Hoar</hi> called his own <hi>Indians, Tom</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and bid the &amp; go and ſee whither he would promiſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192319:36"/>them three: and if he would, he ſhould have it; which he did, and he had it. Then <hi>Philip</hi> ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the buſineſs cal'd me to him, and asked me what I would give him, to tell me ſome good news, and ſpeak a good word for me, J told him, I <hi>could not tell what to give him, I would anothing I had, and asked him what he would have?</hi> He ſaid, two Coats and twenty ſhillings in Mony, and half a buſhel of ſeed Corn, and ſome Tobacco. I thanked him for his love: but I knew the good news as well as the crafty <hi>Fox.</hi> My Maſter after he had had his drink, quickly came ranting into the <hi>Wigwam</hi> again, and called for Mr. <hi>Hoar,</hi> drinking to him, and ſaying, <hi>He was a good man:</hi> and then again he would ſay, <hi>Hang him Rogue:</hi> Being almoſt drunk, he would drink to him, and yet preſently ſay he ſhould be hanged. Then he called for me, I trembled to hear him, yet I was ſain to go to him, and he drank to me, ſhewing no incivility. He was the firſt <hi>Indian</hi> I ſaw drunk all the while that I was amongſt them. At laſt his <hi>Squaw</hi> ran out, and he after her, round the <hi>Wigwam,</hi> with his mony jingling at his knees: But ſhe eſcaped him: But having an old <hi>Squaw</hi> he ran to her: and ſo throngh the Lords mercy, we were no more troubled that night. <hi>Yet</hi> I <hi>had not a comfortable nights reſt: for I think</hi> J <hi>can ſay,</hi> j <hi>did not ſleep for three nights together.</hi> The night before the Letter came from the Council, J could not reſt. J was ſo full of feares and troubles, God many times leaving us moſt in the dark, when delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192319:36"/>is neareſt: yea, at this time I could not reſt, night nor day. The next night I was overjoyed, Mr. <hi>Hoar</hi> being come, and that with ſuch good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. The third night <hi>I</hi> was even ſwallowed up with the thoughts of things, <hi>viz.</hi> that ever I ſhould go home again; and that I muſt go, leaving my Children behind me in the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eep was now almoſt departed from mine eyes.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Tueſday morning</hi> they called their <hi>General</hi> Court (as they call it) to conſult and determine, whether I ſhould go home or no: And they all as one man did ſeemingly conſent to it, that I ſhould go home; except <hi>Philip,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ho would not come among them.</p>
               <p>But before <hi>I</hi> go any further, I would take leave to mention a few remarkable paſſages of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which I took ſpecial notice of in my affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted time.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Of the fair opportunity loſt in the long March, a little after the</hi> Fort-fight, <hi>when our</hi> Engliſh Army <hi>was ſo numerous, and in purſuit of the</hi> Enemy, <hi>and ſo near as to take ſeveral and deſtroy them: and the</hi> Enemy <hi>in ſuch diſtriſs for food, that our men might track them by their rooting in the earth for Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, whileſt they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ying for their lives.</hi> I ſay, that then our Army ſhould want Proviſion, and be forced to leave their purſuit and return homeward: and the very next week the <hi>Enemy</hi> came upon our <hi>Town,</hi> like Bears bereft of their whelps, or ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ravenous Wolves, rending us and our Lambs to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:192319:37"/>death. But what ſhall I ſay? God ſeemed to leave his People to themſelves, and order all things for his own holy ends. <hi>Shal there be evil in the City and the Lord hath not done it? They are not grieved for the affliction of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>therefore ſhal they go Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, with the firſt that go Captive.</hi> It is the Lords doing, and it ſhould be marvelous in our eyes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I cannot but remember how the <hi>Indians</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided the ſlowneſs, and dulneſs of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in its ſetting out. For after the deſolations at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Medfield,</hi> as I went along with them, they asked me when I thought the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army would come after them? I told them I could not tell: It may be they will come in <hi>May,</hi> ſaid they. Thus did they ſcoffe at us, as if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would be a quatter of a year getting ready</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Which alſo I have hinted before, when the</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Army with new ſupplies were ſent forth to purſue after the enemy, &amp; they underſtanding it: fled before them till they came to</hi> Baquaug <hi>River, where they forthwith went over ſafely: that that River ſhould be impaſſable to the</hi> Engliſh. I can but admire to ſee the wonderfull providence of God in preſerving the heathen for farther affliction to our poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. They could go in great numbers over, but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> muſt ſtop: God had an over-ruling hand in all thoſe things.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>It was thought, if their Corn were cut down, they would ſtarve and dy with hunger: and all their Corn that could be found, was deſtroyed, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:192319:37"/>they driven from that little they had in ſtore, into the Woods in the midſt of Winter;</hi> and yet how to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration did the Lord preſerve them for his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ends, and the deſtruction of many ſtill amongſt the <hi>Engliſh!</hi> ſtrangely did the Lord provide for them; that I did not ſee (all the time I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them) one Man, Woman, or Child, die with hunger.</p>
               <p>Though many times they would eat that, that a Hog or a Dog would hardly touch; yet by that God ſtrengthned them to be a ſecurge to his People.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The chief and commoneſt food was Ground-nuts: They eat alſo Nuts and Acorns, Harty choaks, Lilly roots, Ground beans,</hi> and ſeveral other weeds and roots, that I know nor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They would pick up old bones, and cut them to piec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es at the joynts, and if they were full of wormes and magots, they would ſcald them over the fire to make the vermine come out, and then boile them, and drink up the Liquor, and then beat the great end, of them in a Morter, and ſo eat them.</hi> They would eat Horſes guts, and ears, and all ſorts of wild Birds which they could catch: alſo Bear, Venmſon, Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Tortois, Frogs, Squirrels, Dogs, Skunks, Rattle-ſnakes; yea, the very Bark of Trecs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all ſorts of creatures, and proviſion which they plundered from the <hi>Engliſh. I</hi> can but ſtand in admiration to ſee the wonderful power of God, in providing for ſuch a vaſt number of our Enemies
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:192319:38"/>in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> where there was nothing to be ſeen, but from hand to mouth. Many times in a morning, the generality of them, would eat up all they had, and yet have ſome further ſupply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt they wanted. It is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.13, 14. <hi>Oh, that my People bad hearkned to me, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>had walked in my wayes, I ſhould ſoon have ſubdued their Enemies, and turned my hand against their Adverſaries.</hi> But now our perverſe and evil car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages in the ſight of the Lord, have ſo offended him, that inſtead of turning his hand againſt them, the Lord feeds &amp; nouriſhes them up to be a ſcourge to the whole Land.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Another thing that</hi> I <hi>would obſerve is, the ſtrange providence of God in turning things about when the</hi> Indians <hi>was at the higheſt, and the</hi> Engliſh <hi>at the loweſt.</hi> I was with the Enemy eleven weeks and five dayes, and not one Week paſſed without the fury of the Enemy, and ſome deſolation by fire and ſword upon one place or other. They mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (with their black faces) for their own loſſes: yet triumphed and rejoyced in their inhumane, and many times deviliſh eruelty to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> They would boaſt much of their Victories; ſaying, that in two hours time they had deſtroyed ſuch a <hi>Captain,</hi> and his <hi>Company</hi> at ſuch a place; and ſuch a <hi>Captain</hi> and his <hi>Company</hi> in ſuch a place; and ſuch a <hi>Captain</hi> and his <hi>Company</hi> in ſuch a place: and boaſt how many <hi>Towns</hi> they had deſtroyed, and then ſcoffe, and ſay, <hi>They had done them a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:192319:38"/>good turn, to ſend them to Heaven ſo ſoon.</hi> Again, they would ſay, <hi>This Summer that they would knock all the Rogues in the head, or drive them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, or make them flie the Countrey:</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſurely, <hi>Agag-like, The bitterneſs of Death is paſt.</hi> Now the Heathen begins to think all is their own, &amp; the poor Chriſtians hopes to fail (as to man) and now their eyes are more to God, and their hearts ſigh heaven-ward: and to ſay in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, <hi>Help Lord, or we periſh:</hi> When the Lord had brought his people to this, that they ſaw no help in any thing but himſelf; then be takes the quarrel into his own hand: and though they had made a pit, in their own imaginations, as deep as hell for the Chriſtians that Summer, yet the Lord hurll'd them ſelves into it. And the Lord had not ſo many wayes before to preſerve them, but now he hath as many to deſtroy them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to return again to my going home, where we may ſee a remarkable change of Providence:</hi> At firſt they were all againſt it, except my Hu band would come for me; but afterwards they aſſented to it, and ſeemed much to rejoyce in it; ſome askt me to ſend them ſome Bread, others ſome Tobac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, others ſhaking me by the hand, offering me a Hood and Scarfe to ride in; not one moving hand or tongue againſt it. Thus hath the Lord anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my poor deſire, and the many earneſt requeſts of others put up unto God for me. In my travels an <hi>Indian</hi> came to me, and told me, if I were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:192319:39"/>he and his <hi>Squaw</hi> would run away, and go home along with me: I told him <hi>No:</hi> I was not willing to run away, but deſired to wait Gods time, that I might go home quietly, and without fear. And now God hath granted me my deſire. O the wonderfull power of God that <hi>I</hi> have ſeen, and the experience that I have had: I <hi>have been in the midſt of thoſe roaring Lyons, and Salvage Bears, that feared neither God, nor Man, nor the Devil, by night and day, alone and in company: ſleeping all ſorts together, and yet not one of them ever offered me the leaſt abuſe of unchaſtity to me, in word or action.</hi> Though ſome are ready to ſay, J ſpeak it for my own credit; <hi>But I ſpeak it in the preſence of God, and to his Glory.</hi> Gods Power is as great now, and as ſufficient to ſave, as when he preſerved <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions Den; or the three <hi>Children</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u the fiery Furnace. I may well ſay as his <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.12 <hi>Oh give thanks unto the Lord for he is good, for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi> Let the Redeemed of the Lord ſay ſo, whom he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the hand of the Enemy, eſpecially that I ſhould come away in the midſt of ſo many hundreds of Enemies quietly and peacably, and not a Dog moving hi: tougue. So I took my leave of them, and in coming along my heart melted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tears, more then all the while I was with them, and I was almoſt ſwallowed up with the thoughts that ever I ſhould go home again. About the Sun going down, Mr. <hi>Hoar,</hi> and my ſelf, and the two
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:192319:39"/>
                  <hi>Indians</hi> came to <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and a ſolemn ſight it was to me. There had I lived many comfortable years amongſt my Relations and Neighbours, and now not one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to be ſeen, nor one houſe leſt ſtanding. We went on to a Farm houſe that was yet ſtanding, where we lay all night: and a comfortable lodging we had, though nothing but ſtraw to ly on The Lord preſerved us in ſafety that night, and raiſed us up again in the morning, and carried us along, that before noon, we came to <hi>Concord.</hi> Now was I full of joy, and yet not without ſorrow: joy to ſee ſuch a lovely ſight, ſo many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> together, and ſome of them my Neighbours: There <hi>I</hi> met with my Brother, and my Brother in Law, who asked me, if I knew where his Wife was? Poor heart! he had helped to bury her, and knew it not; ſhe being ſhot down by the houſe was partly burnt: ſo that thoſe who were at <hi>Boſton</hi> at the deſolation of the <hi>Town,</hi> and came back afterward, and buried the dead, did not know her. Yet I ws not without ſorrow, to think how many were looking and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and my own Chilren amongſt the reſt, to enioy that deliverance that I had now received: and <hi>I</hi> did not know whither ever I ſhould ſee them again. Being recruited with food and raiment, we went to <hi>Boſton</hi> that day, where I met with my dear Husband, but the thoughts of our dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, one being dead, and the other we could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll where, abated our comfort each to other. I
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:192319:40"/>was not before ſo much hem'd in with the mercileſs and cruel Heathen, but now as much with pittiful, sender-hearted, and compſſionate Chriſtians. In that poor, and deſtreſſed, and beggerly condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I was received in, I was kindly entertained in ſeverall Houſes: ſo much love I received from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral (ſome of whom I knew, and others I knew not] that <hi>I</hi> am not capable to declare it. But the Lord knows them all by name: <hi>The Lord reward them ſeven fold into their boſoms of his ſpirituals, for their temporals.</hi> The <hi>twenty pounds</hi> the price of my redemption was raiſed by ſome <hi>Boſton</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and Ms. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> whoſe bounty and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous charity, I would not forget to make mention of. Then Mr. <hi>Thomas Shepard</hi> of <hi>Charlstown</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us into his Houſe, where we continued ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven weeks; and a Father and Mother they were to us. And many more tender-hearted Friends we met with in that place. We were now in the midſt of love, yet not without much and frequent heavineſs of heart for our poor Children, and other Relations, who were ſtill in affliction. The week following, after my coming in, the Governour and Gouncil ſent forth to the <hi>Indians</hi> again; and that not without ſacceſs; for they brought in my Siſter, and Good-wife <hi>Kectle:</hi> Their not knowing where our Children were, was a ſore tryal to us ſtill, and yet we were not without ſecret hopes that we ſhould ſee them again. That which was dead lay heavier upon my ſpirit, than thoſe which were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:192319:40"/>and amongſt the Heathen; thinking how it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with its wounds, and I was no way able to relieve it; and how it was buried by the Heathen in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> from among all Chriſtians. We were hurried up and down in our thoughts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time we ſhould hear a report that they were gone this way, and ſometimes that; and that they were come in, in this place or that: We kept enquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and liſtning to hear concerning them, but no certain news as yet. About this time the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil had ordered a day of publick <hi>Thanks-giving:</hi> though I thought I had ſtill cauſe of mourning, and being unſettled in our minds, we thought we would ride toward the <hi>Eaſtward,</hi> to ſee if we could hear any thing concerning our Children. And as we were riding along [God is the wiſe diſpoſer of all things] between <hi>Ipſwich</hi> and <hi>Rowly</hi> we met with Mr. <hi>William Hubbard,</hi> who told us that our Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> was come in to Major <hi>Waldrens,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, which was my Siſters Son. I asked him how he knew it? He ſaid, the Major himſelf told him ſo. So along we went till we came to <hi>Newbury;</hi> and their Miniſter being abſent, they deſired my Husband to Preach the <hi>Thanks giving</hi> for them; but he was not willing to ſtay there that night, but would go over to <hi>Salisbury,</hi> to hear fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and come again in the morning; which he did, and Preached there that day. At night, when he had done, one came and told him that his Daughter was come in at <hi>Providence:</hi> Here was
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:192319:41"/>mercy on both hands. Now hath God fulſiled that precious Scripture which was ſuch a comfort to me in my diſtreſſed condition, When my heart was ready to ſink into the Earth [my Children being gone I could not tell whither] and my knees trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled under me, <hi>And</hi> I <hi>was walking thorough the valley of the ſhadow of Death:</hi> Then the Lord brought, and now has fulſilled that reviving word unto me: Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Refrain thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from tears. for thy Work ſhall be rewarded,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and they ſhall come again from the Land of the Enemy.</hi> Now we were between them, the one on the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and the other on the <hi>Weſt:</hi> Our Son being neareſt, we went to him firſt, to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> where we met with him, and with the Major alſo: who told us he had done what he could, but could not redeem him under <hi>ſiven ponnds;</hi> which the good People thereabouts were pleaſed to pay. The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Major, and all the reſt, though unknown ſo me, for their labour of Love. My Sitters Son was redeemed for <hi>four pounds,</hi> which the Council gave order for the payment of Having now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived one of our Children, we haſtened toward the other: going back through <hi>Newbury,</hi> my Husband Preached there on the <hi>Sabbath-day:</hi> for which they rewarded him many fold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>On</hi> Mund ay <hi>we came to</hi> Charlſtown, <hi>where we heard that the Governour of</hi> Road-Iſland <hi>had ſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for our Daughter, to take care of her, being now
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192319:41"/>within his Jurisdiction: which ſhould not paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our acknowledgments.</hi> But ſhe being nearer <hi>Rehoboth</hi> than <hi>Road-Iſland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Newman</hi> went over, and took care of her, and brought her to his own Houſe. And the goodneſs of God was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to us in our low eſtate, in that he raiſed up paſſionate Friends on every ſide to us, when we had nothing to recompance any for their love. The <hi>Indians</hi> were now gone that way, that it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended dangerous to go to her: But the Carts which carried Proviſion to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guarded, brought her with them to <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> where we received her ſafe: bleſſed be the Lord ſor it, <hi>For great is his Power, and he can do whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſeemeth him good.</hi> Her coming in was aſter this manner: She was travelling one day with the <hi>Indians,</hi> with her basket at her back; the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Indians</hi> were got before her, and gone out of ſight, all except one <hi>Squaw;</hi> ſhe followed the <hi>Squaw</hi> till night, and then both of them lay down, having nothing over them but the heavens, and under them but the earth. Thus ſhe travelled three dayes together, not knowing whither ſhe was going: having nothing to eat or drink but water, and green <hi>Hirtle-berries.</hi> At laſt they came into <hi>Providence,</hi> where ſhe was kindly entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſeveral of that <hi>Town.</hi> The <hi>Indians</hi> often ſaid, that I ſhould never have her under <hi>twenty pounds:</hi> But now the Lord hath brought her in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon free-coſt, and given her to me the ſecond
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:192319:42"/>time. The Lord make us a bleſſing indeed, each to others. Now have I ſeen that Scripture alſo fulfilled, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30: 4, 7. <hi>If any of thine be driven out to the outmost parts of heaven, from thence will the Lord thy God gather thee, and from thence will he fetch thee. And the Lord thy God will put all theſe curſes upon thine enemies, and on them which hate thee, which perſecuted thee.</hi> Thus hath the Lord brought me and mine out of that horrible pit, and hath ſet us in the midſt of tender-hearted and compaſſionate Chriſtians. It is the deſire of my ſoul, that we may walk worthy of the mercies recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and which we are receiving.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Family being now gathered together (thoſe of us that were living) the</hi> South Church <hi>in</hi> Boſton <hi>hired an Houſe for us: Then were moved from Mr.</hi> Shepards, <hi>thoſe cordial Friends, and went to</hi> Boſton, <hi>where we continued about three quarters of a year: Still the Lord went along with us, and provided gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly for us.</hi> I thought it ſomewhat ſtrange to fet up Houſe keeping with bare walls; but as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſayes, <hi>Mony anſwers all things;</hi> and that we had through the benevolence of Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friends, ſome in this <hi>Town,</hi> and ſome in that, and others: And ſome from <hi>England,</hi> that in a little time we might look, and ſee the Houſe furniſhed with love. The Lord hath been exceeding good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o us in our low eſtate, in that when we had neither houſe nor home, nor other neceſſaries; the Lord ſo moved the hearts of theſe and thoſe to wards us,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:192319:42"/>that we wanted neither food, nor raiment for our ſelves or ours, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.24. <hi>There is a Friend which ſticketh cloſer than a Brother.</hi> And how many ſuch Friends have we found, and now living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt? And truly ſuch a Friend have we found him to be unto us, in whoſe houſe we lived, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>James Whitcomb,</hi> a Friend unto us near hand, and afar off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I can remember the time, when</hi> I <hi>uſed to ſleep qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly without workings in my thoughts, whole nights together, but now it is other wayes with me.</hi> When all are faſt about me, and no eye open, but his who ever waketh, my thoughts are upon things paſt, upon the awfull diſpenſation of the Lord to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us; upon his wonderfull power and might, in carrying of us through ſo many difficulties, in returning us in ſafety, and ſuffering none to hurt us. I remember in the night ſeaſon, how the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day I was in the midſt of thouſands of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp; nothing but death before me: It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> then hard work to perſwade my ſelf, that ever I ſhould be ſatisfied with bread again. But now we are fed with the fineſt of the Wheat, and, as I may ſay, <hi>With honey out of the rcok:</hi> In ſtead of the Husk, we have the fatted Calf: The thoughts of theſe things in the particulars of them, and of the love and goodneſs of God towards us, make it true of me, what <hi>David</hi> ſaid of himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6. I <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered my Couch with my tears.</hi> Oh! the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull power of God that mine eyes have ſeen, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:192319:43"/>matter enough for my thoughts to run in, that when others are ſleeping mine eyes are weeping.</p>
               <p>I <hi>have ſeen the extrem vanity of this World:</hi> One hour I have been in health, and wealth, wanting nothing: But the next hour in ſickneſs and wounds, and death, having nothing but ſorrow and affliction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before</hi> I <hi>knew what affliction meant,</hi> I <hi>was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſometimes to wiſh for it.</hi> When I lived in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity; having the comforts of the World about me, my relations by me, my Heart chearfull: and taking little care for any thing; and yet ſeeing many, whom I preferred before my ſelf, under ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tryals and afflictions, in ſickneſs, weakneſs, poverty, loſſes, croſſes, and cares of the World, I ſhould be ſometimes jealous leaſt I ſhould have my portion in this life, and that Scripture would come to my mind, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, and ſcourgeth every Son whom he receiveth.</hi> But now I ſee the Lord had his time to ſcourge and chaſten me. The portion of ſome is to have their afflictions by drops, now one drop and then another; but the dregs of the Cup, the Wine of aſtoniſhment: like a ſweeping rain that leaveth no food, did the Lord prepare to be my portion Affliction I wanted, and affliction I had, full meaſure (I thought) preſſed down and running over: yet I ſee, when God calls a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to any thing, and through never ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:192319:43"/>yet he is fully able to carry them through and make them ſee, and ſay they have been gainers thereby. And I hope I can ſay in ſome meaſure, As <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>It is good for me that</hi> I <hi>have been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted:</hi> The Lord hath ſhewed me the vanity of theſe outward things. That they are the <hi>Vanity of vanities, and vexation of ſpirit;</hi> that they are but a ſhadow, a blaſt, a bubble, and things of no continuance. That we muſt rely on God himſelf, and our whole dependance muſt be upon him. If trouble from ſmallar matters begin to ariſe in me, I have ſomething at hand to check my ſelf with, and ſay, why am I troubled? It was but the other day that if I had had the world, I would have given it for my freedom, or to have been a Servant to a Chriſtian. I have learned to look beyond preſent and ſmaller troubles, and to be quieted under them, as <hi>Moſis</hi> ſaid, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Stand ſtill and ſes the ſalvation of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
